有人听到我说话吗？
Anyone hear me?
我能听见你说话。
I can hear you.
谢谢，好的。
Thank you, alright.
我想用今天的讲座来讨论一下线程，
I'd like to spend today's lecture talking about threads
以及 xv6 如何进行线程切换，
and how xv6 does thread switching,
这是关于[xv6]的底层的讲座，
this is a sort of one of the under the hood lectures about [xv6],
我们之前讲过关于系统调用中断，
we've had lectures before about how the system calls interrupts,
页表和锁是如何工作的，
page tables and locks work
今天我们将讨论
and today we're going to talk about
xv6 是如何在不同进程之间切换的。
how does the xv6 switches among different processes.
最高层次的原因是，
The reason for this the highest level reason for this is
因为人们喜欢他们的电脑能够
that people like their computer to be able to
同时完成多项任务，
do more than one task at the same time,
所以原因可能是支持分时，
so the reason might be that you're supporting time sharing,
像 Athena 一样，允许多个用户同时登录，
like Athena allows many users to login at the same time
它们都可以运行进程，
and you know they call run processes
甚至是一台单用户机器，
or even a single user machine
甚至是你的 iPhone ，
or even your iPhone,
你可以运行许多不同的进程，
you may run many different processes
并期望计算机能做你要求它做的所有事情，
and expect the computer to do all the things you ask of it,
而不只是一件事。
not just one thing.
人们喜欢支持多任务的另一个原因是，
Another reason that people like to support multiple tasks is
因为它可以简化程序结构，
because it can ease program structure,
特别是今天的话题线程，
threads in particular today's topic,
有时作为一种方式来帮助人们，
are sometimes used as a way to help people,
帮助程序员以一种简单优雅的方式把程序组合在一起，
to help programmers put together a program in a sort of simple elegant way,
以降低复杂性，
to reduce complexity,
实际上你已经看到了这样的例子，
and you actually saw an example of this
在第一个实验中的素数筛子，
in the first lab with the prime number sieve,
它不使用线程，但使用多个进程，
which didn't use threads exactly but use multiple processes,
为了帮助构建素数筛选软件，
in order to help structure this your prime number sieve software
这是一种更方便、更优雅或更简单的方式，
and arguably it's sort of a more convenient or elegant or simpler way
去写那个软件。
to to write that software.
人们使用线程的最后一个原因是，
And the final reason why people use threads is,
为了从多核机器获得并行加速，
to get parallel speedup from multi core machines,
所以分解你的程序是很常见的，
so it's common to break up your program
使用线程的方式，
in a way that using threads
允许同一程序的不同部分在不同的内核上运行，
to allow different parts of the same program to run on different cores,
也许如果你幸运的话，
and if you can, maybe if you're lucky,
你可以把程序拆分为四个线程运行在四个核心上，
if you can split your program up to run on four threads on four cores,
你也许可以把它的速度提高到原来的四倍。
you might be able to get a factor of four speedup how fast it runs.
实际上，你可以将 xv6 内核视为一个多核并行程序。
And indeed, you can view the xv6 kernel as a multi-core parallel program.
那么线程是什么，
So what threads are,
是一种简化编程的抽象，
is an abstraction to simplify programming,
当你有很多任务时，
when you have many tasks,
当你想要同时处理多项任务时，
when you want to juggle many tasks,
所以线程是什么，
so what a thread is is,
你可以把线程想成一个单一的串行执行，
you can think of a thread as just being a single serial execution,
如果你写一个程序做一件又一件事情，
if you just write a program that does one thing after another,
你运行这个程序，
and you run that program,
你可以把这个程序看作是一种单一的控制线程。
that you know you can view the program as a sort of single thread of control.
所以，这是一个宽泛的定义。
So, this is a loose definition.
因为，人们所说的线程有多种不同的定义，
Because there's many different sort of flavors of what people mean by threads,
但我们说这是一个串行执行，
but we'll say it's one serial execution,
因此，如果你启动一个 CPU ，
so it's what you get if you fire up one CPU
让它用普通的方式一条接一条地执行指令。
and have it you know just execute one instruction after another in the ordinary way.
我们经常谈到线程有状态，
We often talk about thread having state,
因为结果是，
because it's going to turn out,
我们想要保存线程状态，
we're going to want to save away thread state
之后再恢复它，
and restore it later,
所以思考线程状态的正确方式是，
and so the right way to think about thread state,
最重要的部分，
for the most part,
最重要的线程状态的可能是程序计数器，
the most important part perhaps of the thread state is its program counter,
因为它是执行，
because it's an execution,
我们很关心它在执行中的什么位置，
we care a lot about where is it in its execution
它执行指令的地址是什么，
and what address is it executing instructions,
但我们也关心微处理器的其它状态，
but also we care about the rest of the microprocessor state,
这是支持执行所必需的，
that's required to support this execution
所以这意味着它是。
and so that means it's.
线程状态包括编译器用来保存变量的寄存器，
The state of a thread includes the registers that the compiler uses to hold variables
还因为编译器生成代码的方式，
and also because the just the way the compiler generates code,
线程状态包括堆栈，
thread state includes a stack,
所以，一般每个线程都有自己的堆栈，
so typically each thread has its own stack
专用于执行该线程，
dedicated to executing that thread,
堆栈记录函数调用的记录，
and the stack records, the record of function calls,
反映该线程执行中的当前点。
that the reflect the current point in the execution of that thread.
所以， xv6 在其内部包括线程系统，
And so what a threading system xv6 includes a threading system inside it,
线程系统的所做的是，
what a threading system does is
自动执行多个交织的线程，
manage this interleave, automate the interleaving of multiple threads,
你可能希望启动 200 或 400 或 1000 个线程，
you would like to be able to fire up two or 400 or a thousand threads
线程系统会处理所有这些线程，
and the threading system figure out how to juggle all those threads
使它们全部发展，全部执行。
and cause them all to make [progress] and all to execute.
有两个主要的策略，
There's really two main strategy,
我们想要交错，
so we want to [interleave],
这是一个很大的话题，
this is gonna be big topic here,
如何交错多个线程，
how to interleave threads, many threads,
交错执行多个线程的一种方法是
one way to interleave the execution of many threads is
拥有多个 CPU ，
to have multiple CPUs,
像是在多核处理器上，
maybe as on a multi-core processor
然后每个 CPU 可以运行自己的线程，
and then each CPU can run its own thread,
所以如果你有 4 个 CPU ，
so if you have four CPUs,
很明显可以运行 4 个线程，
there's an obvious way to run four threads,
每个 CPU 上运行一个线程，
to run one thread per CPU,
然后每个线程自动获得自己的程序计数器寄存器，
and then each thread automatically gets its own program counter registers,
程序计数器寄存器是与正在运行的 CPU 关联的，
that is the program counter register is associated with the CPU is running on,
但是如果你有 4 个 CPU 和上千个线程，
but if you have four CPUs and you have a thousand threads,
那么如何在核心上使用线程，
then you know how using one core of thread,
不是一个好回答的问题。
is not going to be enough of an answer.
所以，我们看到的另一个主要策略是，
And so the other main strategy that we'll see,
实际上，这节课的大部分内容都是，
indeed the topic of most of this lecture is
每个 CPU 如何在不同线程之间切换，
how each CPU is going to switch among different threads,
所以，如果我有一个 CPU 和上千个线程，
so if I have one CPU and a thousand threads,
我们看看 xv6 是如何构建切换系统的，
we're going to see how xv6 builds switching system,
这允许 xv6 在一段时间内运行一个线程，
that allows xv6 to run one thread for a while
然后切换并放在一边，
and then switch and set aside
保存该线程的状态，
and save the state of that one thread
并切换到第二个线程，执行一段时间，
and switch to executing a second thread for a while
然后是第三个线程，等等，
and then a third thread and so forth,
直到它执行了每个线程的一部分，
until it's executed a little bit of each thread,
然后，返回到第一个线程并继续执行，等等。
and then go back and execute more of the of the first thread and so on.
实际上， xv6 和大多数操作系统，
And indeed, xv6 like most operating system,
xv6 在所有可用核心上运行线程，
[] the xv6 will run threads on all the cores that are available
并且每个核心在线程之间切换，
and each core will switch among threads,
因为通常是，尽管并非总是如此，
because there's typical typically, although not always,
线程数通常比 CPU 数多得多。
there's typically many more threads than there are CPUs.
一个线程系统的不同之处，
One of the many ways in which different threading systems
或者线程系统实例的不同之处是，
or instances of threading systems differ is
是它们否共享内存。
in whether or not they share memory.
所以这是很重要一点。
So this is important point.
一种可能是，你可以有一个单独的地址空间，
One possibility is that you could have a single address space,
许多线程在该地址空间中执行，
with many threads executing in that address space
它们可以看到彼此的变动，
and then they see each other's changes,
如果共享内存的一个线程修改了变量，
if one of the threads sharing some memory modifies variable,
那么其它共享该内存的线程会看到修改。
then the other thread sharing that memory will see the modification.
所以，在线程共享内存的情况下，
And so it's in the context of threads running and sharing memory
我们需要锁，
that we need things like the locks
你在上一节课上看到的。
that you saw in the last lecture.
xv6 内核是共享内存的，
Xv6 kernel is shared memory,
所以 xv6 有，
so xv6, there's,
xv6 支持内核线程的概念，
xv6 has, supports the [notion] of kernel threads,
每个进程有一个内核线程，
there's one kernel thread per process
来执行该进程的系统调用，
that executes system calls for that process,
所有这些内核线程共享内核内存，
all those kernel threads share kernel memory,
所以 xv6 内核线程共享内存。
so xv6 kernel threads do share memory.
另一方面，
And on the other hand,
xv6 还有另一种线程，
xv6 has another kind of threads,
每个用户进程都有一个控制线程，
each user process essentially has a single thread of control,
执行该进程的用户指令，
that executes the user instructions for that process,
实际上， xv6 内核线程机制的一大部分是
and indeed a lot of the xv6 kernel threading machinery is
支持自动地在多个用户进程之间切换，
automatically in support of being able to support and switch them on many user processes,
每个用户进程具有内存，
each user process has a memory
单个线程在其中运行，
and a single thread that runs in that memory,
所以 xv6 用户进程，
so xv6 user processes,
每个进程有一个线程，
each process has one thread
所以在单个 xv6 用户进程内的线程之间不会共享内存，
and so there's no sharing of memory among threads within a single xv6 user process,
因为你有多个进程，
because you get multiple processes,
但是每个进程都是一个地址空间和单个线程，
but each of those processes is an address space with a single thread,
在 xv6 中的进程步共享内存。
the processes in xv6 don't share memory.
在其它更复杂的操作系统中，
In other more sophisticated operating systems,
比如，在 Linux 中，
for example Linux,
Linux 用户级允许在一个进程中有多个线程，
Linux user level does allow multiple threads in a process
并且这些线程共享那个单个进程的内存，
and the processes and those threads share the memory of that single process
这非常酷，如果你想编写用户级的程序，
and that's super cool if you want to write user level programs
用户级并行程序可以使用多核提速，
that user level parallel programs that get speed up from multiple cores
需要另一种，
better requires sort of another,
它使用了很多相同的基础技术，
it uses a lot of the same basic techniques,
我们今天要讨论的，
we're going to talk about today,
但是，在 Linux 实现它有一定的复杂度，
but there's a certain amount more sophistication in Linux to get it,
跟踪每个进程的多个线程，而不只是一个。
keep track of multiple threads per process instead of just one.
好的，从高层次上，我想提一下，
Okay, at a sort of high level, I just want to mention,
还有其他方法，
that there's other ways
可以支持在一台计算机上交错执行多个任务，
to support the interleaving of multiple tasks on a single computer
我们不会讨论它们，
and we're not going to talk about them,
如果你好奇，可以看看事件驱动编程的东西，
if you're curious you can look up things like event-driven programming
或者状态机，
or state machines
它们是非线程技术，
and these are non-thread techniques
在许多不同任务之间共享一台计算机，
to share one computer among many different tasks,
这些是不同层次的不同方案，
it turns out you know sort of on the spectrum of different schemes
为了支持计算机上的多任务，
for supporting multiple tasks on a computer,
线程效率不是很高，
threads are not very efficient,
有更有效的方案，
there's a more efficient schemes,
但是线程通常是最方便的方式，
but threads are usually the most convenient way,
最适合程序员的方式，
most programmer friendly way,
来支持许多不同的任务。
to support lots of different tasks.
好的，这里有几个挑战，
Okay, there's a couple of challenges,
我们必须解决，
that we're gonna have to bite off,
如果我们要实现线程系统。
if we want to implement a threading system.
所以这是高级别的挑战。
The, so this is just high level challenges.
一个是我之前提到的，
One is as I mentioned before,
如何实现交错（线程）的切换，
how to actually implement the switching for interleave,
这个切换允许我们交错执行多个线程，
the switching that allows us to interleave the execution of multiple threads,
这个进程的切换决定有一个广义名称，
and this sort of broad name for this process of switching deciding,
离开一个线程，并执行另一个线程，
or going to leave off one thread and start executing another thread,
这通常称为调度。
it's often called scheduling.
我们将看到 xv6 []的一段代码，
And we'll see that xv6 [] as an actual piece of code,
就是调度器，
that's the scheduler,
实际上，有多个调度器，每个核心一个，
indeed has multiple schedulers one per core,
但是关于如何驱动，
but the general idea of how do you drive,
如何决定从一个切换到另一个，
the decision to switch from one to another,
如何选择要运行的下一个线程，
how to pick the next thread to run,
这就是调度。
its called scheduling.
另一个问题是，
Another question is,
如果你想实现从一个线程到另一个线程的切换，
if you want to actually implement the switch from one thread to another,
你需要保存和恢复，
you need to save and restore,
所以我们需要决定，需要保存什么，
so we need to decide what needs to be saved
保存到哪，
and where to save it,
当我们离开一个线程时，需要保存它，
when, it needs to be saved when we leave off executing one thread
并在稍后想要重新执行该线程时，恢复它，
and restored when we want to resume executing that thread at some later time,
最后一个问题是，如何处理计算密集型线程。
and final question is what to do about compute bound threads.
很多选择，
The, many of the options,
很多切换线程的直接的选择，
many of the most straightforward options for thread switching
引入线程自愿表示，
involve the threads are voluntarily saying
我要保存自己的状态，
well I'm going to save away my state
让另一个线程运行，
and sort of run another, let another thread be run,
但是，如果我们有一个用户程序做长时间的计算，
but what do we have a user program that's doing some long running calculation,
可能需要几个小时，
that might take hours,
它不会特别考虑，
it's not going to be particularly thinking about,
现在是时候让别的线程运行了，
oh now be time to good time to let something else run,
所以最方便是，通过某种方式
so it's most convenient to have some way of
自动从长时间运行的计算密集型进程收回控制权，
sort of automatically revoking control from some long running compute bound process,
把它放在一边，之后再运行。
setting it aside and maybe running it later.
好的，我要谈谈这些，
Alright, so I'm going to talk about these,
实际上，首先我要谈谈，
I'm actually going to talk about
处理计算密集型线程的机制。
the machinery for dealing with compute bound threads first.
而且，方案就是你以前知道的，
And, scheme for that is something you've come up before,
那就是定时器中断。
that's timer interrupts.
这里的想法是，
And the idea here is that,
每个核心，每个 CPU 上都有一个硬件，
there's a, a piece of hardware on each CPU on each core,
它会产生周期性的中断，
that generates periodic interrupts,
而 xv6 或任何操作系统
and the xv6 or any operating system
将这些中断传送给内核，
really arranges to have those interrupts delivered to the kernel,
所以，即使我们在用户级运行一些循环，
so even if we're running at user level at some loop
比如计算 pi 的前 10 亿位，
that's you know computing the first billion digits of pi,
尽管如此，定时器中断还是会在某个时间点发生，
nevertheless the timer interrupts go off at some point
可能是每 10 毫秒一次，
maybe every ten milliseconds
将控制从该用户级代码转移到
and transfer control from that user level code
内核中的中断处理程序，
into the interrupt handler in the kernel,
这是内核获得控制权的第一步，
and so that's the first step in the kernel being able to gain control
用来在不同的用户级线程之间切换，
to switch among different user level processes, user level threads,
即使那些用户级线程不是协作的。
even if those user level threads aren't cooperative.
基本方案是，在中断处理器中，
And the basic scheme is that in the interrupt handler,
所以我们有处理这些程序的内核中断。
so we're gonna have you know kernel handler for these interrupts.
我们会看到，
And we'll see,
内核处理程序让出，
that the kernel handler yields,
这个名称是 yields ，
this is the sort of name for this it yields,
内核处理程序自愿让出 CPU 给调度器，
the kernel handler sort of voluntarily yields the CPU back to the scheduler
告诉调度器，你现在可以运行其他线程。
it tell the scheduler look, you can let something else run now.
而这个让出是一种线程切换的形式，
And this yields is really a form of thread switch,
它保存了当前线程的状态，
that saves away the state of the current thread,
这样以后就可以恢复。
so it can be restored later.
我们会在这里看到整个流程，
And we'll see the full story here,
实际上，你已经在这里看到了整个流程，
actually you've seen a lot of the full story here,
因为它涉及到中断，
because it involves an interrupt,
你已经知道整个流程有些复杂，
what you already know about the full story some complex,
但是基本的想法是定时器中断
but the basic idea is that a timer interrupt
将控制权交给内核，
gives control to the kernel
而内核自愿让出 CPU ，
and the kernel voluntarily yields the CPU,
这个术语称为抢占调度。
this is called as a piece of terminology preemptive scheduling.
它的意思是，
And what that means is that,
抢占的意思是，
the preemptive means is that,
即使正在运行的代码不愿意，
even if the code that's running doesn't, you know doesn't want to,
没有明确地让出 CPU ，
you know doesn't explicitly yield the CPU,
定时器中断会夺走控制权，
the timer interrupt is going to take control away
我们会让出给它，
and we're going to yield for it
抢占式调度的反义词称为自愿式调度。
and the opposite of preemptive scheduling might be called maybe voluntary scheduling.
有趣的事情是，
And the interesting thing is that
抢占式调度在 xv6 等操作系统中的实现是
the the implementation in xv6 and other operating systems of preemptive scheduling is
定时器中断强制夺取 CPU ，
this timer interrupt forcibly takes away the CPU
然后内核自愿让出，
and then the kernel basically does a voluntary yield
切换到那个进程的线程。
thread thread switch on [have] of that process.
这里出现的另一个术语是，
Now, another just piece of terminology that comes up here is
当线程运行时，
that while the threads running,
有必要区分，
there's need to distinguish,
系统区分当前在某些 CPU 上运行的线程，
systems that distinguish between threads that are currently actually running on some CPU
与想要运行，但当前没有在任何 CPU 上运行的线程，
versus threads that would like to run, but aren't currently running on any CPU,
但是如果 CPU 空闲就可以运行，
but you know could run if a CPU became free
与那些实际上不想运行的线程，
versus threads that actually don't want to run,
因为它们在等待 IO ，
because they're waiting for IO
或者在等待什么事件。
or waiting for some event.
这种区别通常称为状态，
And [] this distinction is often called state,
即使线程的完整状态
even though the full state of the thread is
要比这复杂得多。
actually much more complicated than that.
既然说到这件事，
Since this is going to come up,
我想列出几个我们会看到的状态，
I just want a list out a couple of states that will be seeing,
这些是 xv6 管理的状态，
and these are states that xv6 maintains,
有一种状态是 RUNNING ，
there's a state called RUNNING,
意味着它正在某个 CPU 上运行，
which means it's actually executing on some core, some CPU right now,
有 RUNNABLE ，意味着目前没有在任何地方运行，
there's RUNNABLE, which means not currently executing anywhere,
但是有保存的状态，想要尽快运行，
but just a saved state, but would like to run as soon as possible
然后还有一个状态，
and then it turns out there's a state,
今天不会讲太多，但是下周会讲到，
which won't come out much today, but will come up next week,
叫做 SLEEPING ，表示线程等待某个 IO 事件，
called SLEEPING, just means the threads waiting for some IO event
只有在 IO 事件发生之后运行，
and only wants to run after the IO event occurs,
所以今天我们关注的运行时和可运行线程，
so today we're mostly concerned with running and runnable threads
这个抢先切换所做的，
and what this preemptive switch does,
这个定时器中断和 yield 所做的是，
what this timer interrupt does and the yield is
将一个运行时线程，
basically convert a running thread
即被定时器中断的线程，
whatever thread was interrupted by the timer
转换为一个可运行线程。
into a runnable thread.
这是一个线程，
That is a thread,
通过让出或转换为另一个线程，
that's by yielding or converting that thread into a thread,
它现在没有运行，
that's not running right now,
但很明显它将会运行，
but would actually like to clearly,
因为它在计时器中断时运行。
because it was running at the timer timer interrupt.
好的，那么，
Okay so,
运行的线程的程序计数器寄存器在 CPU 中，
running thread its program counter registers are actually in the CPU,
在执行它的 CPU 的硬件寄存器中，
you know in the hardware registers of the CPU that's executing it,
可运行线程没有，
a runnable thread though has no,
它现在没有关联的 CPU ，
it's now doesn't have a CPU associated with it
所以，我们需要保存，
and therefore we need to save,
对于可运行状态，我们需要保存所有 CPU 状态，
for every runnable state, we need to save whatever CPU state,
任何线程运行时的 CPU 使用的状态，
whatever state the CPU was keeping when that thread was running,
所以我们需要复制 CPU 的内容，
so we need to copy the CPU contents,
不是 RAM ，只是寄存器，
you know which is not RAM, but just registers really,
从 CPU 到内存中的某个地方以保存它们，
from the CPU into memory somewhere to save them,
当我们将线程从运行时转为可运行的时候。
when we turn to thread from running to runnable.
再说一次，我们必须明确保存的状态，
And again this is the basically the state we have to explicitly save yours,
只有 CPU 的运行状态，
just the state, the executing state of the CPU,
也就是程序计数器和 CPU 寄存器，
which is the program counter and registers at CPU,
所以这些需要保存，
so these need to be saved,
当将线程转换为可运行的。
only convert a thread to runnable.
当某个调度器决定运行可运行线程时，
When some scheduler finally decides to run a runnable thread,
那么，作为再次运行该线程的步骤一部分，
then as part of the many steps in getting that thread going again and resuming it,
我们会看到程序计数器，
we're going to see that the program counter,
保存的程序计数器寄存器被复制回 CPU ，
the saved program counter registers are copied back into the CPUs,
到调度器决定运行线程的 CPU 的寄存器上。
actual register on the CPU that the scheduler decides to run it on.
好的，关于这些术语有什么问题吗？
Alright, any questions about these terminology?
好的，我要，
Alright, I'm gonna,
现在讨论一下 xv6 的东西。
now sort of talk about a sort of more xv6 [] view of things.
我要画两张图，
I'm gonna draw two pictures,
关于线程和 xv6 ，
really of threads and xv6
一张是简单图，一张是更详细的图。
are kind of simplified picture and a more detailed picture.
像往常一样，用户的东西在上面，
So as usually the user stuff up here
内核在下面。
and the kernel down here.
我们可能在用户级别运行多个进程，
We might be running multiple processes at user level,
也许是 C 编译器、 ls 和 shell ，
maybe you know the C compiler and ls and shell,
它们可能同时或不同时运行，
they may or may not be all wanting to run at the same time,
在用户级别，每个进程都有，
at user level, each of these processes has,
它有内存，
you know it has memory,
我们特别感兴趣的是，
and of particular interest to us,
每个进程都有用户堆栈，
each of these processes has a user stack,
当它运行时，它在 RISC-V 硬件中有寄存器，
and while it's running it has registers in the RISC-V hardware,
PC 和寄存器。
so PC plus registers.
好的，当程序运行时，
Alright, so while programs running,
有一个在用户级别运行的控制线程，
you know there's essentially a thread of control that's running at user level
我要说的是，
and the way I'm going to talk about it is,
就像有一个用户线程，
as if there's a user thread,
包含用户堆栈，用户内存，用户程序计数器，用户寄存器，
that consists of the user stack, user memory, user program counter, user registers,
如果程序访问系统调用，
if the program makes a system call,
中断并进入内核，
interrupted and goes into the kernel,
然后这些东西保存在这个程序的 trapframe 中，
then this stuff saved away in this program's trapframe
并且这个程序的内核线程被激活，
and a kernel, the kernel thread for this program is activated
现在， trapframe 保存着用户的东西，
and so now this is the trapframe hold saved user stuff
在我们保存了用户程序计数器寄存器之后，
after we saved a way the user [] program counter registers,
然后，我们将 CPU 切换到使用内核堆栈。
then we switch the CPU to using the kernel stack.
我们不需要恢复寄存器，
And you know we don't need to restore registers,
因为，进程的内核线程并没有真正运行，
because, through the the kernel thread for process isn't really running,
当用户线程运行时，它没有实际的保存状态，
it has no real save state, when the user thread is running
相反的，内核线程在其堆栈上激活。
instead it's sort of the kernel thread is kind of activated on its stack.
所以，第一次在 trampoline 和用户 trap 代码。
So the first time in in the trampoline and a user trap code.
然后内核运行一段时间，
And then the kernel runs for a while,
也许是系统调用或中断处理程序，
maybe running a system call or interrupt handler,
不管是什么，
whatever it maybe,
有时，系统调用只是简单地返回，
and sometimes it is a system call particular will just simply return,
从这里到同一个进程，
from this point back to the same process
返回到用户空间，或者恢复该程序的程序计数器寄存器，
and return to user space or restore this program's program counter registers,
但也可能不是简单地返回，
but it could also be that instead of simply returning,
而是因为这样或那样的原因，
for one reason or another,
可能是因为定时器中断，
maybe because it was a timer interrupt,
我们要切换到另一个进程，
we're actually going to switch to another process
高层次的观点是，
and the very high-level view of that is that
如果 xv6 调度器决定从这个进程切换到不同进程，
if the xv6 scheduler decides switch from this process to a different process,
发生的第一件事是，
what the first thing that really happens is
我们要切换内核线程，
that we're going to switch kernel threads
从这个进程的内核线程到另一个进程的内核线程，
from this processe's kernel thread to the other process's kernel thread,
然后其他进程的内核线程返回到用户空间。
and then the other processes kernel thread will return back to user space.
所以，假设 C 编译器需要读取磁盘，
So supposing that the C compiler [] needs to read the disk
所以它会让出 CPU ，
and so it's going to yield the CPU
休眠并等待磁盘完成，
while sleeping to wait for the disk to complete,
也许 ls 想要执行，并处于可运行状态，
maybe ls wants to execute and is in runnable state,
xv6 调度器可能做的是，
what the xv6 scheduler maybe they do is that,
如果 ls 处于可运行状态，
well, if ls is in runnable state,
意味着它在某个地方停了下来，
that means it left off somewhere
它的状态保存在一边，可能是因为定时器中断，
and its state was saved away possibly by a timer interrupt
所以 ls 有一个保存的 traframe ，
and so ls will actually have a saved trapframe
包含用户寄存器和它自己的内核堆栈，
with user registers and its own kernel stack,
它保存了一些与内核线程有关的寄存器，
and as it turns out save set of kernel registers associated with the kernel thread
这被称为上下文。
which is going to be called the context.
所以，如果 xv6 从编译器内核线程切换到 ls 内核线程，
So, if xv6 switches from the compiler kernel thread to ls's kernel thread,
xv6 将保存内核寄存器，
xv6 will save away the kernel registers,
在 C 编译器内核线程切换到 ls 线程的上下文中，
in a context with a C the compilers kernel thread switch to the ls thread,
这个复杂的方案，我稍后会描述，
complex scheme which I'll describe a little bit later,
我们恢复 ls 的内核线程寄存器，
we'll restore ls's kernel thread registers
从上一次停止的 ls 上下文中，
from the previously save context from one ls last left off,
也许 ls 完成正在执行的系统调用，
maybe ls will finish whatever system call was executing,
在 ls 的内核线程堆栈上，
you know on the ls's kernel thread stack,
然后返回到 ls 系统调用，
and then return back to ls system call,
在返回用户空间的路上，
on the way to return to user space
它将为 ls 恢复以前保存的用户寄存器，
that will restore these previously saved user registers for ls
然后继续执行 ls 。
and then resume executing ls.
所以，这里有一堆我们将要讨论的细节，
So, there's bunch of details here which we'll talk about,
但也许这里的重点是，
but maybe the main point here is that
在 xv6 中，我们不会看到用户到用户的上下文切换，
we never in xv6 see direct user to user context switches,
当我们从一个进程切换到另一个进程，
when we're switching from one process to another,
总是一种策略，
always the sort of strategy
xv6 从一个进程切换到另一个进程是，
by which xv6 switches from executing one process to another process is
跳入内核，保存进程状态，
you jump in the kernel, saves the process state,
从这个进程的内核线程切换到另一个进程的内核线程，
run this process's kernel thread switch to the kernel thread of another process,
那个进程暂停了自己，
that suspended itself
然后返回并恢复用户寄存器，
and then return and restore user register,
所以一直是这种间接的策略，
so it's always this indirect strategy,
实际上比这更间接的，
actually even more indirect than this,
对于线程切换，
to threads swhich,
实际结果是从一个用户进程切换到另一个用户进程。
where the net effect is to switch from one user process to another user process.
关于这张图，有什么问题吗？
Question about this diagram or anything?
切换，调度器，发生在这两个之间，对吗。
Switched the scheduler, that happens in between those two, right.
是的，好的，让我来谈谈调度器，
Yep, all right, let me talk about the scheduler,
实际图片要比这复杂得多。
so the real picture is actually a significantly more complex than that.
这是更完整的图，
This is a may or more, gonna be more full diagram,
假设我们有进程一 P1 正在运行，
let's say we have process one which is executing,
而进程二 P2 是可运行的，但是现在没有运行，
and process two which is runnable, but not currently running,
还有一些额外的细节，
now the additional layer of details,
我们在 xv6 中有多个核心，
we actually have multiple cores in xv6,
假设我们有两个核心，
let's say we have two cores,
这意味着在硬件层面上，
so that means that at the hardware level,
我们有 CPU0 ，它是其中一个核心，
we have CPU0 which is one of the cores
还有 CPU1 。
and let's say CPU1.
更完整的故事是
And the more full story about
我们如何从执行用户空间到，
how we get from executing user space to,
在用户空间中执行的一个进程，
in one process executing in user space
到另一个可运行但没有运行的进程，
in another runnable but not yet running process,
第一部分与我所说的相同，
the first part is about the same as I talked about
定时器中断强制
and may say a timer interrupt forces
将控制从用户进程转移到内核，
transfer control from the user process into the kernel,
trampoline 代码保存进程一的用户寄存器和 trapframe ，
the trampoline code saves the user registers and trapframe for process one,
然后执行 usertrap ，
and then executes usertrap
它知道该怎么处理这个 trap 或中断，
which figures out what to do with this trap or interrupt,
系统调用，比如，
you know system call, let's say as a,
所以有段时间，我们执行普通的内核 C 代码，
so for a little while, we're executing ordinary kernel C code,
在进程一的内核堆栈上。
on the kernel stack of process one.
假设，进程一的内核代码决定让出 CPU ，
Let's say process one, the kernel code process once decides it wants to yield the CPU,
它有一堆东西，我们可以看到细节，
it has a bunch of things, which we'll see the details of,
最终调用这个例程切换，
that end up in a call to this routine switch,
是这个故事中的一个中心例程，
just sort of one of the central routines in this story,
switch 保存上下文，
switch saves away this context,
在上下文一中运行的内核线程的寄存器，
that registers for the kernel thread that's running in context one,
所以有两组用户寄存器，
so there's two sets of registers,
用户寄存器， trapframe ，内核线程寄存器在上下文中。
the user registers, the trapframe, the kernel thread registers in the context.
switch 不会，
Switch doesn't actually,
switch 从一个线程切换到另一个，
switch switches from one content from one thread to another,
但是实际上 xv6 的设计方式，
but in fact the way xv6 is designed,
用户线程，
the only place that a user thread,
抱歉，在 CPU 上运行的内核线程可以切换的唯一位置是，
sorry, the kernel thread running on a CPU can switch to is
那个 CPU 的调度器线程。
what's called the scheduler thread for that CPU.
所以我们甚至不能直接切换到另一个进程，
So we can't even switch directly to another process,
只能切换到调度器线程，
can only switch to the scheduler thread,
所以这里有一个，
so there's a,
完整的线程装置专用于 CPU0 的调度器，
the complete thread apparatus dedicated to the scheduler for CPU0,
因为我们使用的是 CPU ，
since we're running on CPUs,
这个 switch 会切换到调度器线程的之前保存的寄存器，
this switch is going to switch to the previously saved registers for the scheduler thread,
假设是调度器 0 。
so let's say schedule zero.
在 CPU0 的调度器中，
And in the scheduler for CPU0,
switch 会，通过恢复这些寄存器，
switch will, by restoring these registers,
由于寄存器包括堆栈指针，
since registers include the stack pointer,
正如我们看到的， switch 的返回，
the return from switch as we see,
将会返回到 CPU0 上的调度器函数，
will now actually return up to the scheduler function on CPU,
调度器函数会进行一些清理，
and scheduler function will do some cleanup
使进程一进入休眠状态，
to finish putting process one to sleep,
然后它在进程表中查找另一个进程，
then it'll look in the process table for another process,
一个可运行进程，
a runnable process,
如果它找到了一个，
and if it finds one,
所以我们从这里下来，然后到调度器，
and so we've sort of gone down here and up into the scheduler,
如果调度器找到另一个要运行的进程，
if the scheduler finds another process to run
或者发现进程一是可运行的，并且仍然想要运行，
or even finds process one is runnable and still wants to run,
找到进程一，没有别的进程想要运行，
find process one nothing else nothing else wants to run,
但不管怎样，调度器会再次调用 switch ，
but in any case, the scheduler will call switch again,
将上下文切换到进程二，
to switch contexts to say process two,
在线程中， switch 再次保存自己的寄存器到自己的上下文中，
in the process switch will save its own registers again in its own context,
它们也会是前序保存的上下文，
they'll be a previously saved context too,
当进程而停止时，
from whenever process two left off
这组寄存器将被恢复，
that those this set of registers will be restored,
进程二将使用前序调用，
process two will have made a previous call,
像进程一样，切换到调度器线程，
to switch, to switch to the scheduler thread just like process one did
当它停下来的时候，
when it left off,
它调用 switch 返回
that called a switch return to,
无论系统调用还是中断，
whatever system call or interrupt,
进程二结束，
process two is end, when that's finished,
会有一个先前保存的进程二的 trapframe ，
there will be a previously saved trapframe for process two,
它将包含用户寄存器，
that will contain user registers,
也可以恢复或返回到用户空间。
also be restored or return back up into user space.
每个 CPU 都有一个完整的、单独的调度器线程，
And there's a complete, a separate scheduler thread for each CPU,
所以，它们也将被保存，
so, they'll also be saved,
CPU1 的调度器线程的上下文，
context for the scheduler thread for CPU,
以及在调度器一上运行的调度器循环，
and a scheduler loop running on scheduler one
以及任何运行在 CPU1 上的进程，比如进程三或其他，
and whatever process, you know process three or something is running on CPU one
当它决定让出 CPU 时，
when it decides to give up the CPU,
它将切换到 CPU 为它的调度器线程。
it'll switch into scheduler thread for it for its CPU.
好的，这里有一个问题，
Alright, there's a question,
上下文存储在哪里，
where the context stored,
对于这些我刚才说的操作，
it turns out that for the operations I've been talking about,
保存的，
the saved,
事实上，对于线程切换，
in fact always the for a thread switch,
这些上下文，这些内核线程保存的寄存器
these contexts, these saved register sets for kernel threads,
都在进程结构体中，
all in the process structure,
所以，任何内核线程只能有一组保存的内核寄存器。
so any given kernel thread can only have one set of saved kernel registers.
因为每个线程只在一个位置执行，
Because each thread is only executing a single place
它的上下文在某种程度上反映了它执行的位置，
and its context kind of reflects that place that it was executing on it left off
线程是单个控制线程，
a thread is a single thread of control,
所以一个线程只需要一个寄存器的上下文，
so a thread really only needs one context for registers,
所以，它在进程结构体的 p->context 。
so it's in the process structures p arrow, p->context.
而且每个调度器线程都有自己的上下文，
And the scheduler, each scheduler thread has its own context
不是在，
which actually not in the,
没有与调度器线程关联的进程，
there's no process associated with this scheduler thread,
调度器的上下文存储在核心的 CPU 结构体中。
this is actually scheduler's context is stored in the struct CPU for that core.
有一组 CPU 结构体，每个核心一个，
There's an array of these CPU's struct one per core,
每一个有一个上下文。
each one has a context.
为什么我们不能将寄存器包括在进程的 trapframe 中，
Question, why can't we include the registers in the trapframe for the process,
实际上，这些寄存器可以存储在 trapframe 中，
that is, you know actually the those registers could be stored in the trapframe
因为只有一个内核线程寄存器的存储集，
which may, because there's only one save set of kernel thread registers,
对于进程，我们可以将它们保存在任何数据结构中，
for process, we could save them in any data structure
比如存在进程数据结构实例的一个元素，
for which there's one element of instance of that data structure process,
只有一个进程结构，
there's one struct process,
有一个用于进程的 trapframe 结构，
there's one struct trapframe for process,
我们可以把寄存器保存在 trapframe 中。
we could store the registers in the trapframe.
我是说，只是，
I mean just sort of for,
可能是为了代码的简单性或清晰性，
maybe simplicity or clarity of code,
trapframe 只包含数据，
the trapframe I think, entirely consists of data,
进入和离开内核时需要的（数据）。
that's needed when entering and leaving the kernel.
content 结构由需要保存和恢复的内容组成，
And the struct context is consists of the stuff that needs to be saved and restored,
当内核线程和调度器线程之间切换时。
when switching to and from between the kernel thread and the scheduler thread.
好的，问题是，
Okay, question is,
yield 是有内核调用的，
yield something that's called by the user of the kernel, called by the kernel,
所以在 xv6 中，用户线程没有真正直接的方式，
so the user threads, there's not really a direct way in xv6
用户线程让出 CPU 或切换，
for user threads to talk about, yielding the CPU or switching,
它是通过内核这种透明的完成，
that it's done by the kernel kind of transparently,
它会在内核觉得有必要发生的时候出现，
you know it points in time when the kernel feels that it needs to happen,
如果有线程，
if there are threads,
有时候，你能猜到，
there are sometimes when, you can sort of guess
一个系统调用可能让出，
that probably a certain system call will result in yield,
比如，如果进程在管道上进行读取，
like if a process does a read on a pipe,
它知道在管道中没有需要等待读取的东西，
where it knows that really nothing is waiting to be read in that pipe,
那么读取就会阻塞，
then the read will block,
你可以预测读取阻塞，
you can predict the read block
内核将运行其他进程，
and that the kernel will run some other process,
当我们等待数据出现在管道中时。
while we're waiting for data to appear in the pipe.
所以，内核调用 yield 的时机，
So the times when yield is called in the kernel,
有两个主要的时机，
there's really two main times,
一种是如果计时器中断，内核总会让出，
one is if a timer interrupt goes off, kernel always yields,
基于这样的理论，
you know just on the theory that,
我们应该交错执行所有这些进程，
we should interleave the execution of of all the process
想要定期在定时器中断时运行，
that want to run on timer interrupt periods,
所处，定时器中断总是调用 yield ，
so timer interrupt also always calls yield
当进程系统调用等待 IO 时，
and whenever a process system calls waiting for IO,
等待你输入下一次按键，
waiting for you know type the next keystroke,
读取控制台，
does a read of the console
但是你没有按键，
and you haven't typed key yet,
然后等待 IO 调用的机器调用 yield ，
then the the machinery to wait for IO calls yields,
调用 sleep ，我们下周会谈到。
called for sleep, something we'll talk about next week.
好的。
Alright.
好的，那么。
Okay, so.
我有一个问题。
I have another question.
好的。
Yes.
如果是 sleep ，
Oh, if it is a sleep,
它是否会做大致相同的事，
is it gonna do the same thing roughly,
比如会是系统调用，
so it's gonna be some system call,
保存 trapframe ，
there's gonna save the trapframe
然后是一样的[图片]，
and then basically the same [picture],
但它只是，
but it's just then the thing
使进程在没有定时器中断的情况下进入内核，
that made the process go into the kernel without a timer interrupt,
但是，是进程自己决定的吗？
but, the process's own decision?
是的，所以这个进程有一个读取系统调用，
Yeah, so the process make there's a read system call
这就是为什么它在内核中，
and that's why it's in the kernel,
而读取需要这个进程等待磁盘完成读取，
and the read requires the process to wait for the disk to do to finish reading
或者等待数据出现在管道上，
or to wait for data to appear on a pipe,
那么图跟这个是一样的，
then actually the diagram is exactly the same as this,
内核中调用系统调用，
and the kernel with a system call,
trapframe ，所有保存的用户寄存器，
trapframe, all the saved user register,
执行系统调用，系统会[]，
execute the system call, the system will [],
需要等待磁盘完成读取某些内容，
need to wait for the disk to finish reading something,
系统调用调用 sleep ，包含 switch ，
the system call code will call sleep which ends up coding switch,
保存进程上下文中的内核线程寄存器，
which saves away the kernel thread registers in the process context
切换到该当前 CPU 调度器，
switches to this current CPU scheduler,
让其他线程运行，
to let some other thread run,
而这个线程等待磁盘读取完成。
while this thread is waiting for the disk read to finish.
所以，我们现在谈论的一切，
So everything we're going to talk about now,
除了定时器中断，
except for the timer interrupt,
几乎都是一样的，
is pretty much the same
如果发生的情况是我们使用系统调用，
if what's going on is we're in a system called,
系统调用需要等待一些 IO ，
the system call needs to wait for some for IO
并放弃 CPU 。
and give up the CPU.
对于今天的讨论，
For the purposes of today's discussion,
这两种情况几乎是一样的。
the two situations are almost identical.
好的，问题是每个 CPU 调度器都有自己的堆栈吗。
Okay, so the question does each per CPU scheduler has its own stack.
是的，
Yes,
这里有一个堆栈，
there's a stack,
而这个调度器有单独的堆栈，
this scheduler stack for this separate stack,
对于 CPU1 的调度器。
for scheduler for CPU one.
是的，这个调度器的堆栈也设置好了，
Yeah, and indeed the stacks for this scheduler also setup,
实际上，所有这些东西，
in fact, all this stuff
上下文，堆栈，调度器线程，
you know the context and the stacks with a scheduler threads
设置与用户进程的设置方式不同。
are set up in a different way than for user process's.
它们是在引导时设置的，
They're set up at boot time,
如果查看 start.S 或 start.c ，
if you poke around and start.S or start.c, start.S probably,
你会看到每个核心的调度器线程的设置，
you'll see some of the setup for each core's scheduler thread,
堆栈在引导的汇编代码中非常早的位置，
there's a place with stack very early in the assembly code during boot,
其中为每个 CPU 设置堆栈，
where the stack is set up for each CPU
在那个堆栈上，
and it's on that stack,
CPU 引导，
that's a CPU boots on
然后运行它的调度器线程。
and then runs its scheduler thread.
好的，嗯。
Okay, um.
一条行话，
One piece of jargon,
当人们谈论上下文切换时，
when people talk about context switch,
他们谈论的通常是这种行为，
they're talking about usually this act of
从一个线程切换到另一个，
switching from one thread to another
保存旧线程的一组寄存器，
by saving one set of register sets for the old thread
并且恢复要切换到的线程先前保存的寄存器，
and restoring previously saved registers for the threads were switching to,
这就是上下文的意思，
that's what's usually meant by context,
有时它也适用于完整的，
which also sometimes it's applied to the complete done is
一个用户进程切换到另一个，
that goes on when switching from one user process to another
偶尔会看到在用户和内核之间切换的上下文，
and occasionally you'll see context which apply to switching between user and kernel,
但对我们来说，我们大多数的意思是，
but for us we mostly mean it,
从一个内核线程切换到调度器线程。
switching from one kernel thread typically to scheduler thread.
只是一些片段信息，
Just some pieces of information,
要记住的[][]，
the [] [] to keep in mind,
每个核心一次只做一件事，
every core just does one thing at a time,
每个核心在任何时间只运行一个线程，
each core you know is either is just running one thread at any given time,
它要么运行一些用户线程或一些内核线程，
it's either running some processes user thread some process kernel thread
或核心的调度器线程，
or that core's scheduler thread,
所以在任何时间，核心都不会做多件事，
so at any given time the core is not doing multiple things,
它只是在做一件事，
it's just doing one thing
正是这种切换在创造了一个假象，
and it's this switching that sort of creates the illusion
多个线程在核心上不同时间运行，
of multiple threads running at different times on that core,
类似地，每个线程运行在，
similarly, each thread is running on,
要么在一个核心上运行，
is either running on exactly one core
或它的状态已保存，
or its state has been state has been saved
然后我们从它切换走。
and we switched away from it.
所以，一个线程，
So, so a thread,
线程不会在多个核心上运行，
just to be clear, thread never runs on more than one core,
线程要么在一个核心上运行，
thread is either running on just one core
要么根本没有运行，作为保存状态。
or it's not running at all, as a saved state somewhere.
另一个关于 xv6 设置的有趣的事情是，
Another interesting thing about the xv6 setup is that
这些上下文保存内核线程寄存器，
these contexts that hold saved kernel thread registers,
它们总是由调用 swtch 产生，
they're always produced by a call to switch
所以，这些上下文总是关联指线程的状态，
and so these contexts basically always refer to the state of the thread
它在对 swtch 的调用中执行的。
and it was executing inside a call to swtch.
我们会看到的方式是，
And you know the way we'll see that come up is that
当我们从一个切换到另一个，
when we switch from one to another
并恢复目标线程的上下文，
and restore the target thread's context,
它要做的第一件事是从上一个调用返回到 swtch ，
the first thing it will do is return from a previous call to swtch,
这些上下文总是保存状态，
these contexts are always saved state,
就像它在 swtch 里一样。
in as it is in swtch.
好的。
Okay.
关于图表级别的情况，还有什么问题吗？
Any more questions about the diagram level situation?
我有一个问题，
I have a question,
你一直使用线程这个术语，
you are using the term thread all the time,
但在我看来，我们对 xv6 的实现，
but it seems to me, like our implementation for xv6,
一个进程只有一个线程，
a process is if there's only one thread,
所以，有没有可能一个进程可以有多个线程，
so it could it be possible that one process could have multiple threads
还是我说错了。
or am I wrong here.
在 xv6 中，好的。
In xv6, alright.
我们在这里的说法是有一些让人困惑的地方，
There's definitely some confusing things about the way we use the words here,
在 xv6 中，
in xv6,
一个进程，
a process,
一个进程执行用户级别的指令，
a process is either executing instructions user level
或者执行内核中的指令，
or it's executing instructions in the kernel
或者根本不执行，
or it's not executed at all
它的状态被保存到上下文和 trapframe 中。
and its state has been saved away into this combination of context and trapframe.
所以这就是实际情况，
So that's the actual situation,
你怎么叫它，
which you want to call that,
你想怎么叫都行，
you call it what you like,
我不知道对这个结构有什么简单的解释，
I I don't know of a simple explanation for this structure,
我们一直这样叫它，
we've been calling it I've been calling it,
我一直说每个进程有两个线程，
I've been saying that each process has two threads,
一个用户级线程和一个内核级线程，
a user level thread and a kernel level thread
这是一个进程，
and that's a process,
有这样的限制，
there's this restriction
进程只会执行，
that a process is only execute,
或者在用户空间的内核中执行，
either executing in the kernel in the user space
或者在内核中中断系统调用中，
or executing in the kernel, inter- interrupt system call,
但不能两个同时。
but never both.
理解了。
That makes sense.
是的，我为这件事的复杂性道歉。
Yeah, I apologize for the complexity of this.
好的。
Okay.
好的，让我切换到代码，
Okay, so let me switch to code,
看看 xv6 代码。
looking at the xv6 code.
好的，首先，
Alright, so first of all,
我展示一些我们一直在谈论的东西，
I just wanna, just show some of the stuff we've been talking about,
我来看一下进程的结构。
I'm going to look at the process structure.
我们可以在进程结构中看到，
And we can see in the process structure,
很多东西我们已经讨论过，
a lot of the things we've been talking about,
复习一下，
just for review,
这是 trapframe ，保存了用户级别寄存器。保存用户级寄存器的陷阱帧。
there's the trapframe, that saves the user level registers.
这里有一个上下文，它保存内核线程寄存器，
There's a context here, that saves the kernel thread registers,
当切换到调度器线程。
which switch to the scheduler thread.
有一个指向这个进程的指针是内核堆栈，
There's a pointer to this process is kernel stack,
保存函数调用的位置，
which is where function calls are saved,
当我门在内核中执行时。
while we're executing in the kernel.
这是状态变量，
There's the state variable,
它记录该进程是否正在运行或是否可运行，
which records whether this process is running or runnable
或者处于休眠状态或根本没有分配。
or sleeping or not allocated at all.
最后，这里有一个锁，保护我们看到的各种东西，
And then finally, there's a lock that protects various things as we'll see,
目前，我们可以看到，至少保护了对状态变量的更改。
for now, we can observe that at least protects changes to the state variable.
比如，两个调度器线程，
So that for example two scheduler threads,
不会试图获取一个可运行的进程并同时运行它。
don't try to grab a runnable process and run it at the same time.
这个锁做的事情之一就是防止这种情况发生。
One of the many things this lock does is prevent that from happening.
我要为你们运行一个简单的演示程序 spin 程序。
I'm gonna run a simple demo program for you, the spin program.
我要用它来推动，
I'm using it mostly just to drive the
创造一种可预测的情况，
sort of create a predictable situation
我们从一个线程切换到另一个线程，
in which we switch from one thread to another,
但这就是这个程序，
but this is this program,
spin 程序创建了两个进程，
spin program creates two processes
而且这两个过程都是永远计算的，
and the processes both compute forever,
在这里调用 fork，
you know call fork here,
我创造了一个子程序，
I make a child
然后两个子程序永远在这个循环里，
and then forever, both children both children just sit in this loop
而每个进程打印一个字符，
and everyone's while print a character,
所以，我们可以看到它们的进展，
so we can see they're making progress,
但是它们不经常打印字符，
but they don't print characters very often,
而且它们从来不会故意放弃 CPU 。
and they never sort of intentionally give up the CPU.
所以我们这里有两个计算密集型进程，
So what we have here is two, essentially two compute bound processes
为了让它们两个都跑起来，
and in order for both of them to run,
我将在单个 CPU 上运行它们，
I'm gonna run them on a single CPU,
只有一个核心的 xv6 ，
xv6 that is only one core
所以，为了让它们两个都能执行，
and so in order for both of them to execute,
有必要在这两个进程之间切换。
you know it's going to be necessary to to switching between the two processes.
让我使用 gdb 把 spin 程序启动起来，
Let me fire up spin program under gdb,
运行 spin 程序，你可以看到它在打印，
run the spin program and you can see it's printing,
其中一个进程打印正斜杠，
one of the two processes prints forward slash
另一个打印反斜杠，
and the other prints backward slash
你可以看到，每隔一段时间，
and you can see that every once in a while,
xv6 在它们之间切换，
xv6 is switching between them
而且只有一个核心，就像我配置的那样，
and only has one core the way I've configured it,
所以我们看到打印一堆正斜杠，
so we see a bunch of forward slashes printing
然后很明显是计时器中断，
and then apparently a timer interrupt,
将一个 CPU 切换到另一个进程，
must go off switch the one CPU to the other process
然后打印一会另一种斜杠。
and then prints the other kind of slash for a while.
所以，我想要观察的是计时器中断的运行，
So what I want to observe is the timer interrupt going off,
所以我要在 trap 里放一个断点，
so I'm gonna put a breakpoint in trap,
尤其是在 trap 中的第 207 行，
and in particular at line 207 in trap,
trap 中的 devintr 代码，
which is a code in trap in devintr,
表示我们在中断中，
that recognizes that we're in interrupt
并且这是中断是由定时器中断引起的。
and the interrupt was caused by a timer interrupt.
所以我在这里设置一个断点，
So I put a breakpoint here,
在 trap.c 第 207 行，
at trap.c 207
继续[]我刚才触发的 trap ，
and continue [boom] the trap I triggers right away,
因为定时器中断相当频繁，
because timer interrupt are pretty frequent
我们可以从得到，
and we can tell from
用户 trap 调用 devintr 的地方，
where that indeed when user trap and user trap has called devintr
来处理这个中断。
to handle this interrupt.
我想离开 devintr ，回到用户 trap 中。
I wanna take finish to get out of devintr back into user trap.
因为，事实上我们没有，
Because, in fact we don't,
devintr 到定时器中断的代码没有什么东西。
the code devintr into timer interrupt you know says almost nothing.
然而，一旦我们回到 usertrap ，
However, once we're back at in usertrap,
我们可以从这一行看到，
we can see that this line here,
我们刚从 devintr 返回。
that we just returned from devintr.
有趣的是，
And the interesting thing about this is that,
我们接下来要做的，
what we're about to do,
期待我们在这一行，
I'm looking forward we're currently at this line here
我们期待这里调用 yield ，
and we're looking forward to this call the yield,
在这里你可以看到， devintr 返回了 2 ，
when devintr return two, you can see from this,
返回的是 2 ，
the return is two,
2 是设备号，
two is basically the device number
我们很快就会看到这一点，
and we're going to see that by and by,
因为哪个设备是 2 ，
because which devices two,
usertrap 要 yield 的，
usertrap going to call yield,
它获得 CPU 并允许运行进程，
which go to CPU and allows [pushing] the process,
你很快就会看到这一点，
you'll see that in a moment,
同时，让我们看看中断发生时正在执行的是什么。
meantime let's look at what was currently executing when the interrupt happened.
我要打印 p ，
I'm going to print p,
变量 p 保存着指向当前进程结构 proc 的指针。
the variable p holds a pointer to the current processes struct proc.
好的，问题是什么让每个进程的内核线程不同。
Okay, the question what makes each processes kernel thread different.
每个进程都有单独的内核线程，
Every process has a separate kernel thread,
确实有两个不同的进程内核线程，
there's really two things that differentiate different processes kernel thread,
因为多个可以在不同的核心上执行。
because more than one could be executing on different cores.
一个是每个进程都有单独的内核堆栈，
One is indeed that every process has a separate kernel stack
就是结构体 proc 的 kstack 所指向的，
and that's what's pointed to by that kstack element of struct proc
另一个是，
and the other is that,
早些时候，
early in,
当 usertrap C 代码调用时，
when usertrap which is you know the C code is called,
通过 trampoline ，当中断发生时。
by trampoline, when interrupt occurs.
我们可以通过任何内核代码区分它们，
We can tell by this call them by any, any kernel code,
可以通过调用 myproc 来判断当前 CPU 上正在运行哪些进程。
can tell by calling myproc what the processes is running on the current CPU.
这是另一个不同的地方，
And that's another thing that differentiates,
这允许内核代码区分，
that allows each, that allows kernel code to tell
哪个进程内核线程正在执行，
what process it's part of that is which processes kernel thread is executing
而 myproc 使用的是 tp 寄存器，
and what myproc does basically use the tp register
你可能还记得，
which you may recall,
设置为包含当前核心 hartid 或核心编号，
is set up to contain the current cores hartid or core number,
使用它来索引到一个结构数组，
it uses that to index into an array of structures,
也就是说，对于调度器设置的每个核心，
that say for each core that the scheduler sets
每当它切换进程以指示每个核心，
whenever it switches processes to indicate for each core
哪个进程在那个核心上运行。
which process is running on that core.
这就是不同内核如何区分。
And so that's how different kernels are differentiated.
好的，我要使用这个 p 的值，
Okay, so I was going to use that p value,
名称和 p 值以确定哪个进程正在运行，
the name and that p value to figure out what process is running,
xv6 记得名字就是 spin 进程，像预期的一样，
xv6 remembers the name it's that spin process just exactly as expected,
有两个进程，我想进程 id 分别是 3 和 4 。
there were two of them, I think with process ids three and four.
糟糕。
Oops.
我们现在再次执行进程 3 ，
We're currently executed again process id three,
所以在切换之后，我们应该在进程 4 中，
so after the switch we'd expect to be in process id four,
另一个 spin 进程，
the other spin process,
我们可以查看 trapframe 中保存的用户寄存器。
and we we can look at the saved user registers in the trapframe.
这是 32 个寄存器，
And these are the 32 registers
trampoline 代码保存用户状态，
that a trampoline code saves a way to save the user state,
用户 ra 返回用户堆栈指针的地址，
there's the user ra return address register user stack pointer,
用户寄存器是十六进制 62 。
user program counter at hex 62.
这些都是我们在观察 trap 时熟悉的东西。
These are familiar things from when we looked at traps.
你可能最感兴趣的是，
And you may be the most interest is that,
trapframe 保存着用户程序计数器和值 62 ，
the trapframe saves the user program counter and that value 62,
如果我们关心，可以查看 spin.c 的汇编代码。
if we cared, we can look in the assembly code for spin.c.
糟糕，在 spin.asm 查找 62 ，
Oops, spin.asm look for 62,
我们可以看到有一个中断定时器，
now we can see that owes a interrupt timer,
中断发生在 spin 无限循环中的加法指令期间，
interrupt occurred during this add instruction in that infinite loop in spin,
这并不令人惊讶。
so it's not too surprising.
好的，回到刚才返回的 trap 代码，
Okay, so back to a trap code [] just returned,
我要单步几次把我们带到，
I'm going to take step a few times to get us to the,
到达执行 yield 。
just being about to execute this yield.
而 yield 是进程中让出 CPU 的第一步，
And yield is sort of the first step in the process of giving up the CPU
切换到调度器，
switching to the scheduler,
让调度器选择进程中的另一个内核线程来运行。
letting the scheduler choose another kernel thread in process to run.
好的，让我们单步进入 yield ，
Alright, so let's actually step into yield,
现在我们在 yield ， yield 是。
now we're in yield, yield's.
你有什么问题吗。
If you have a question.
不是。
No.
好的，我们在 yield 中，
Okay, we're in yield,
yield 做了几件事，
yield does a couple of things,
它获取这个进程的锁，
it acquires the lock for this process,
因为它要对这个进程进行一系列的修改，
because it's about to make a bunch of changes to this process,
而且它不希望有任何其他的，
and it doesn't want any other
实际上，在它放弃锁之前，
and in fact until it gives up the lock,
这个进程的状态会是一致的，
the state of this process will be sort of in consistent
比如， yield 将进程的状态更改为可运行，
like for example, it's about yield is about to change the state of the process to runnable,
这表明，
which would you know indicates that,
这个进程没有在运行，但希望运行，
the process is not running, but would like to,
但是这个进程是在运行的，
but this process is running, right,
我是说，我们正在运行这个进程，
I mean we're running the process right now,
就是正在执行的这个进程的内核线程，
that's what's executing is the kernel thread for this process
所以，获取这个锁所做的事情之一是，
and so the one of the many things that acquire this lock does is,
让它，尽管我们修改状态为可运行，
makes it, so that even though we just changed the state runnable,
没有其他核心的调度线程会看到这个进程，
no other core's scheduling thread will look at this process
因为使用了锁，
and because of lock
（其他核心）看到它是可运行的，并试着运行它，
and see that it's runnable and try to run it
当我们还在这个核心上运行它时，
while we're still running it on this core,
将会是一场灾难，
would be a disaster right,
在两个不同的核心上运行相同的进程，
running the same process on two different cores,
你知道进程只有一个堆栈，
you know process has only one stack,
这意味着两个不同的核心在同一个堆栈上调用[子例程]，
so that means like two different cores are calling [subroutines] on the same stack,
这是一个灾难。
which is just a [recipe] for disaster.
所以，我们使用了锁，
So we take the lock out,
yield 把状态改为可运行。
we, yield changes the state to runnable.
这意味着，
And what this mean is that,
我们最终放弃了，
you know we finally given up the,
当我们最终放弃 CPU ，
when we finally yield the CPU and given it up
切换到调度器进程，
and switch the scheduler process,
这个状态会保持在可运行状态，
this state will be left in this runnable state,
这样它就可以再次运行，
so that it will run again,
毕竟这是一个计时器中断，
because after all this was a timer interrupt,
中断了正在运行的用户级进程，
that interrupted a running user level process,
它希望继续运行。
that would like to continue computing.
我们把状态设置为可运行，
We're gonna leave state runnable,
让它可以再次运行，
so that it will run again,
一旦调度器做了决定。
as soon as the scheduler decides to.
然后，另一件事情是，
And then, the only other thing that,
yield 调用了这个调度器函数。
yield does is call this scheduler function.
所以，我要单步执行调度器函数。
So I'm going to step into the scheduler function.
我会在这里展示整个过程。
I'll show this whole thing here.
这个调度器几乎什么都不做，
This scheduler is something does almost nothing,
它做了一些检查，
it does a bunch of checks,
它做了一些可用性检查和 panic ，
it does a whole bunch of sanity checks and panics
这个原因是，
and the reason for that is actually that,
xv6 中的这段代码，
this code in xv6,
在多年的时间中，一直是最容易出错的，
over its many year lifetime had been among the most bug [prone]
有最多的意外，不愉快的意外，
and have most surprises unhappy surprises,
所以这里有很多可用性检查和 panic ，
so there's a lot of sanity checks and panics here,
因为经常会有与这些代码相关的 bug 。
because, because there's often bugs associated with this code.
好的，我会跳过这些可用性检查，
Alright, I'm gonna skip over these sanity checks
然后继续到调用 swtch ，
and proceed to the call to swtch,
这个调用 swtch 是真正的操作发生的地方，
this call to switch is where the real action happens,
这个调用 swtch ，
this is call the switch
将保存目前的内核线程寄存器到 p-> context 中，
is going to save away the current kernel threads registers in p->context,
是当前进程保存内核线程上下文，保存寄存器，
which is the current process's saved kernel thread context, save set of registers,
c->context ， c 是指向核心 CPU 结构的指针，
c->context, c is the pointer to this core's struct cpu,
CPU 结构体具有保存这个核心调度器线程的寄存器的上下文，
struct cpu has context to save registers of this core's scheduler threads,
我们将从这个线程切换，
we're going to be switching from this thread
保存这个线程的状态，
and saving this thread state,
恢复核心调度器的线程状态，
restoring the thread state of this core's scheduler
并继续运行这个核心的调度器线程。
and continuing the execution of this core's core's scheduler thread.
好的，让我们看看是，
Okay, so let's see what,
让我们快速看一下上下文，
let's take a quick preview at the context
我们将切换到的，
that we're going to be switching to
我可以得出，
and I can get that turns out that,
我不能直接打印 c->context ，
I can't actually print c->context,
但我知道 c 打印 cpus[0] ，
but I happen to know that c prints to cpus zero,
因为我们在核心 0 上，
just because we're on the zero with core,
只有一个核心，
there's only one core,
我可以打印它的上下文。
and I can print its context.
这就是这个核心的调度器线程中保存的寄存器。
And so this is the saved registers from this core's, scheduler thread.
特别感兴趣的是 ra ，
And of particular interest is the ra,
因为 ra 寄存器是当前函数调用要返回的地方，当前函数调用将返回到，
because the ra register is where the current function call is going to return to,
所以我们要切换调度器线程，
so we're going to switch the scheduler thread,
它会返回，并返回到 ra 。
it's going to do return and return to that ra.
我们可以找到，
And we can find out
通过查看 kernel.asm ，找到那个返回地址。
where that where that return address by looking in kernel.asm.
实际上，那是。
Actually that's.
你可以看到的，这个 x/i ，
And as you can see this x/i,
打印某个地址的指令，
you know prints instructions that at a certain address,
但它也会打印函数的名称标签，
but it also prints the label of the name of the function
那些指令在这个函数里面，
that those instructions are in it,
所以我们很快会回到调度器上，
so we're going to be returning to scheduler by and by,
这正是你希望的。
that's just you know as you might expect.
好的。
Okay.
我想看看 swtch 做了什么，
I want to look at what swtch actually does,
关于调用 swtch 。
about to call swtch.
所以我在 swtch 上设置一个断点，
So I put a breakpoint on swtch
设置断点，
and putting a breakpoint,
因为这里有一堆设置代码，
because there's a bunch of setup code
将上下文的值从这些结构中提取出来，
that pulls the values of context out of those structures,
我会跳过它。
I'll skip over it.
好的，现在，
Okay, so now,
当到达 swtch 断点时，
when a breakpoint at swtch,
GDB 不会给我们看指令，
the gdb won't show us the instructions,
但是我们可以查看 switch.S ，
but we can look at switch.S
来查看即将执行的指令。
to look at the instructions we're about to execute.
正如你看到的，我们在第一条指令，
So as you can see we're on the very first instruction,
将 ra 保存到 a0 指向的地址，
the store of ra to the address pointed to by a0,
你可能还记得在调用 swtch 中，
you may remember in the call to swtch,
第一个参数是当前线程的上下文，
that the first argument was the current thread's context
第二个参数是我们要切换到的线程的上下文，
and the second argument was the context of the thread we're switching to,
两个参数分别到 a0 和 a1 。
the two arguments going a0 and a1.
所有保存都要通过寄存器 a0 的原因是，
And so the reason why we see all these stores through register a0 is
是因为我们在 a0 指向的内存中保存了一堆寄存器，
because we're storing away a bunch of registers in the memory that a0 points to
是我们切换的线程的上下文，
that is in the context of the thread we're switching from
而加载从地址 a1 中加载，
and the loads load from address a1,
因为这是指向我们要切换到的线程的上下文的指针。
because that's a pointer to the context of the thread, we're switching to.
好的，线程， swtch 保存寄存器，加载寄存器，
Okay, and so thread, you know, swtch saves registers, loads registers
从目标线程的上下文中，然后返回，
from the target thread's context and then return
这就是为什么 ra 很有趣，
and that's why the ra was interesting,
因为它返回 ra 指向的位置，即进入调度器。
because it's going to return to the place that ra pointed to namely into scheduler.
好的，这里有一个问题，你可能会注意到，
Alright, so one question is you may notice here
虽然 swtch 保存了 ra sp 和很多 s 寄存器，
that while swtch saves ra sp and a bunch of s registers,
却没有保存程序计数器，
one that does not save is the program counter,
这里没有提到程序计数器，
there's no mention of the program counter here,
那是为什么。
so why is that.
是不是因为程序计数器在函数任何时候调用时都是更新的。
Is it because the program counter is updated with like the function calls anyway.
是的，程序计数器里没有实际的信息值，
Yeah it's it's the program counter, there's no actual information value in the program counter,
我们知道正在执行的是 swtch 。
we know that we're executing right now is in switch, right.
因此没有保存程序计数器，
So there be no point in saving the program counter,
因为它有一个可预测的值，也就是这条指令，
because it has an extremely predictable value namely this instruction,
swtch 指令的地址，
the address of this instruction of swtch
我们真正关心的是我们从哪里被调用，
what we really care about is where we we're called from,
因为当我们切换回这个线程时，
because when we switch back to this thread,
我们希望继续从调用点执行，
we want to continue executing out whatever points swhich was called from
它就是 ra ，
and it's ra,
保存着调用 swtch 指令的地址。
that holds the address of the instruction that swtch was called from.
所以是 ra 被保存在这里，
So it's ra, that's being saved away here,
而 ra 是再次执行的点。
and ra is the point at which will be executing out again.
让 swtch 返回，
Let's swtch return,
我们甚至可以打印，
so we even print that we can print,
ra ，糟糕。
ra, oops.
我们可以打印 ra ，
We can print ra
我们还没有切换线程，
and you know we haven't actually switched threads yet,
还记得我们是从这个 sched 函数过来的，
you remember we came here from this sched function,
所以，如你所想的， ra 指向 sched 函数。
so ra as you might expect the pointer back into this sched function.
另一个问题是，
Another question is,
为什么 swtch 只保存了 14 个寄存器，
how come swtch only saves 14 registers,
我数了一下，
I counted them,
它只保存和恢复 14 个寄存器，
it only saves and restores 14 registers,
尽管 RISC-V 有 32 个寄存器，
even though the RISC-V has 32 registers
可用于，代码可以使用。
available for the or use it for code to use.
为什么只保存了一半的寄存器？
Why, why only half the registers are saved?
当调用 swtch 时，它是作为正常函数调用的，
Well, when swtch was called, it was called as a normal function,
所以，任何调用 swtch 都会假设 swtch 可能会修改这些，
so whoever called swtch already assumed will swtch might modify those,
以便那个函数将其保存在它的堆栈中，
so that that function already saved that on its stack,
这意味着当我们从一个跳到另一个的时候，
meaning that like when we jump from one to the other,
它会自动恢复调用者保存寄存器。
that one is gonna self restore its caller save registers.
完全正确，
That's exactly right,
这个 swtch 是由 C 代码调用的，
the swtch are called from C code,
我们知道 C 编译器保存在当前堆栈上，
we know that the C compiler saves on the current stack,
任何调用者保存寄存器，
any caller saved registers,
包含编译器之后需要的值。
that have values in them that the compiler's going to need later.
而那些调用者保存寄存器包括，
And those caller saved registers actually include,
我想有 18 个，
I think there's 18,
取决于你如何计算它们，
depending on how you count them,
有 15 到 18 个调用者保存寄存器，
there's somewhere between fifteen and eighteen caller saved registers,
所以，我们在这里看到的寄存器是所有不是调用者保存的寄存器，
so the registers we see here are all the registers that aren't caller saved
编译器没有保证保存，
and that the compiler doesn't promise to save,
但是仍然可以保存调用函数所需的值，
but nevertheless may hold values that are needed by the calling function,
所以当我们切换线程时，只需要保存被调用者保存的寄存器。
so we all need to save the callee saved registers, when we're switching threads.
好的。
Okay.
我想打印的最后一个东西是，
Final thing I want to print is the,
我们保存和恢复了堆栈指针，
we do save and restore the stack pointer,
当前堆栈指针，很难从这个值判断，
the current stack pointer, it's like hard to tell from this value,
这意味着，它是当前进程的内核堆栈，
what that means, that it's the kernel stack of the current process,
我不知道你是否记得，
which I don't know if you recall,
但是是由虚拟内存系统在高内存映射的。
but is allocated is mapped by the virtual memory system at high memory.
好的，我们要保存当前的寄存器，
Okay, so, okay, so we're going to save away the current registers
从调度器线程的上下文中恢复寄存器，
and restore registers from scheduler thread's context,
我不想执行每一个加载或保存，
I don't want to execute every single one of these load or store,
所以我要跳过，
so I'm gonna step over,
所有这 14 个保存和 14 个加载，
all the 14 loads, the 14 stores and the 14 loads,
直接到返回指令。
going to proceed directly to the return instructions.
好的，所以我们执行了 swtch 中的所有代码，除了返回，
Okay, so we executed everything in swtch, except the return,
在我们返回之前，
before we do the return,
我们再次打印感兴趣的寄存器，
we'll just print the interesting registers again,
看看我们在哪里。
to see where we are.
所以堆栈指针，现在它有一个不同的值，
So stack pointer, now it has a different value,
堆栈指针现在指向内存中的堆栈零区域，
stack pointer now points into this stack zero area in memory,
这是在引导序列中非常早的位置，
and this is actually the place it very very early in the boot sequence
在 start.S 中放置堆栈，
where start.S puts the stack,
以便它可以调用第一个 C 函数，
so it may call the very first C function,
所以回到这个 CPU 的初始引导堆栈，
so actually back on the original boot stack for this CPU
它恰好就是调度器运行的地方。
which just happens to be where the scheduler runs.
好的，我们对程序计数器也很感兴趣，
Okay, the program counter actually interesting,
我们在 swtch 中，因为我们还没有返回，
we're in swtch because we haven't returned yet
并且现在 ra 寄存器指向调度器，
and the ra register now points the scheduler,
因为我们已经加载，
because we've loaded,
我们已经恢复了之前由调度器线程保存的寄存器集。
we've restored the register set previously saved by the scheduler thread.
实际上，我们现在在调度器线程中，
And indeed, we're really now in the scheduler thread,
如果我执行 where ，
if I run on where,
返回结果跟上次执行完全不一样了，
the where now looks totally different from the last time we ran,
它现在是调用 swtch ，
it were now indeed a call to swtch,
但是现在我们调用 swtch ，
but now we're in a call from swtch
要切换到过去某个时间调度器，
to switch the scheduler may at some point in the past
调度器很久以前就在引导期间运行了，
and the scheduler was run long ago during boot
是在引导过程中所调用的最后一件事。
was called as the last thing that [] did during the boot process.
所以，我要执行一条指令，从 swtch 返回到调度器。
So I'm gonna ask you know one instruction to return from switch now into scheduler.
现在我们在这个内核的调度器中，
So now we're in this core's scheduler,
看看完整的代码，
look the full code,
这是调度器代码，
so this is the scheduler code,
这个函数叫做 scheduler ，
this function called scheduler,
现在我们在 CPU 调度器线程中执行，
now we're executing in the scheduler thread for the CPU,
我们在，
and we're just at the point,
我们从之前的调用返回到 swtch ，
we just returned from a previous call to swtch
它是调度器在之前创建的，
the scheduler made a while ago,
当它决定开始运行这一进程时，
when it decided it was going to start running that process,
pid 3 ，它是被中断的 spin 进程，
you know pid 3 which was the spin process that was interrupted,
所以现在这个 swtch 进程 id 是 3 ，
so now it's this swtch process id 3,
是 spin 调用的 swtch ，
that's spin called swtch,
但这次返回的不是之前的 swtch ，
but it's not swtch that swtch this returning
之前的 swtch 还没有返回，
last swtch hasn't returned yet
仍保存在进程 id 3 堆栈和上下文中，
is still saved away in process id three stack and context
只是从先前的 swtch 返回。
just return from this earlier called swtch.
好的，在调度器中发生的事情，
Alright, so the stuff that happens here in the scheduler,
已停止运行这个进程，
were stopped running this process
所以你可以忘掉我们所做的各种事情，
and so you want to forget about the various things we did,
在运行这个进程的过程中，
in the process of running this process,
我们希望[忽略] c->proc 等于零，
we want to [forget] the c->proc equals zero,
意味着我们忘了这个。
basically means that we're forgetting that.
我们不再在这个核心中运行这个进程，
We're no longer running this process in this core's,
所以我们不想让任何人对此感到困惑，
so we don't want to have anybody be confused about that,
让我把每个核心进程指针设置为零，
let me set this per core proc pointer to zero [] this process,
接下来发生的事情是，
the next thing that happens is that,
你记得 yield ，获取这个进程的锁，
you remember yield, acquired the lock for this process,
因为它不想任何其他核心调度器
because it didn't want any other core's scheduler
看到这个进程并可能运行它，
to look at this process and maybe run it
直到这个进程完全进入休眠状态。
until the process was completely put to sleep.
我们现在已经完成了从这个进程的切换，
We've now completed the switch away from this process,
这样我们可以释放对刚刚让出的进程的锁，
so we can release the lock on the process that just yield,
这就是 release ，
that's the release,
在这一点上，我们还在调度器中，
at this point, we're still in the scheduler,
如果还有另一个核心，
if there was another core,
在这时，其他核心调度器可以找到这个进程，
at this point, some other core's scheduler could find that process,
因为它是可运行的，并运行它。
because it's runnable and run it.
不过，没关系，
But that's okay,
因为我们已经完全保存了它的寄存器，
because we've completely saved its registers,
不再在那个进程堆栈上执行，
we're no longer executing on its that processes stack,
因为现在在这个核心的调度器堆栈上执行，
because now executing on the this core's scheduler stack,
所以，如果其他核心决定运行这个进程，也没什么问题。
so it's actually fine if some other core decides to run that process.
好的，但是这里没有其他核心，
Okay, but there's no other core,
所以在这个演示中并没有发生。
so that doesn't actually happen in this demonstration.
实际上，我想花点时间再谈一下 p->lock ，
Actually, I want to spend a moment talking about the p->lock a little bit more,
p->lock 做了几件事，
p->lock actually does a couple of things,
从调度器的角度来看，它做了两件事，
it does really two things from the point of view of scheduling,
一个是让出 CPU ，
one is that yielding the CPU,
涉及多个步骤，
involves multiple steps,
我们必须设置状态为可运行的，
we have to set the state to runnable,
将状态从运行中改为可运行，
change the state from running to runnable,
我们将寄存器保存在让出进程的上下文中，
we save the registers in the yielding processes context,
现在我们必须停止使用让出进程的堆栈，
now we have to stop using the yielding processes stack,
至少有三个步骤，
there's at least three steps,
需要时间来做这些步骤让出 CPU ，
which take time in order to do all the steps required to yield the CPU
所以锁做的一件事是，
and so one of the things that lock does
正如我提到的，
as I mentioned is
阻止任何其他核心调度器看到我们的进程，
prevent any other core scheduler from looking at our process
直到所有三个步骤完成之前，
until all three steps have completed,
所以锁是把这些步骤变成原子性的，
so the lock is basically making those steps atomic,
从其他核心的角度来看，它们都发生，
they either all happened from the point of view of other cores,
或者它们都不发生。
or none of them happened.
当我们开始运行一个进程时，
It's going to turn out also when we start running a process
p->lock 也具有类似的保护功能，
that the p->lock is going to have a similar protective function,
我们将进程的状态设置为运行中，
we're going to set the state of a process to running,
当我们开始执行进程时，
when we start executing a process
我们把它的寄存器从它的进程上下文转移到 RISC-V 寄存器中，
and we're going to move its registers from its process context into the RISC-V registers,
但是，如果在进程中间发生中断，
but, if an interrupt should happen in the middle of that process,
中断会看到进程处于一种奇怪的状态，
the interrupt going to see the process in a weird state
比如状态标记为运行中，
like maybe in the state of mark running,
但是没有完成将寄存器从上下文移动到 RISC-V 寄存器，
but hasn't yet finished moving its registers from the context into the RISC-V registers,
那将是一场灾难，
and that would be a disaster,
如果发生定时器中断，
if a timer interrupt happened in,
因为我们可能会离开这个过程，
because we might switch away from that process,
在它恢复寄存器之前。
before it had restored its registers.
从这个进程中离开，
And switching away from that process
会保存未初始化的 RISC-V 寄存器到进程的上下文，
would save now uninitialized RISC-V registers into the context process's context,
覆盖它的真正的寄存器。
overwriting its real registers.
所以，实际上，我们也希望启动一个进程具有原子性，
So indeed we want starting a process that also be effectively atomic,
在这种情况下，持有一个锁，
and in this case holding a lock,
在切换到进程的过程中持有 p->lock ，
holding p->lock across switching to a process
为了防止其他核心看到这个进程，
as well as preventing other cores from looking at that process
还会在切换到那个线程的[]持续时间内关闭中断，
also turns off interrupts for the duration of [firing] up of switching to that thread
防止定时器中断看到，
which prevents a timer interrupt from ever seeing
只切换到一半的进程。
a process that's only midway through being switched to.
好的。
Okay.
所以我们在调度器中，
So we're in the scheduler,
我们在调度器的循环中执行，
we're executing this loop in the scheduler's,
调度器中的循环，依次查看所有进程，
loop in the scheduler's that looks at all the process
以找到一个要运行的进程，
in turn to find one to run
在这种情况下，我们知道还有另一个进程，
and in this case, we know there's another process,
因为，还有另一个我们 fork 的 spin 进程，
because, there's that other spin process that we've forked,
但是有很多东西要检查，
but there's a lot of process lots to examine,
我将跳过扫描进程表，
I'm going to skip over the actual process scanning of the process table
直接调到到调度器找到下一个进程的点，
and go direct to the point of which, the scheduler finds the next process,
所以我要把断点放在第 474 行，
so I'm gonna put a breakpoint at line 474,
在那里它找到了一个要运行的新进程。
where it's actually found a new process to run.
[]在这里，调度器扫描进程表，
[] here we are, the schedulers scan the process table
并找到另一个要运行的进程。
and found another process to run.
它会调用那个进程运行，
And it's going to call that process run,
你可以看第 468 行，
you can see a line 468,
它获取了那个进程锁，
it acquired that process's lock,
所以现在它有权做不同的步骤，
so now it's entitled to do the various steps
切换到那个进程，
were required to switch to that process,
在第 473 行，它将进程状态设置为运行中，
in line 473, it set the process of state to running,
现在是第 474 行，
it's now at 474,
我们在 CPU 结构中记录 CPU 正在执行的进程，
we're going to record in the CPU structure which process the CPU is executing
然后调用 swtch 来保存调度器的寄存器，
and then call swtch to save the scheduler's registers
并恢复目标处理器的寄存器，
and restore the target processor's registers,
你可以看到找到了什么进程，
so you can see what process is found
通过查看新的进程名称，
by looking at the new process name,
当然它是 spin ，
surprisingly its spin,
它的进程 id 现在是 4 ，
it's process id is now four,
以前是 3 ，现在是 4 。
used to be running three now running four.
我们已经将状态设置为运行中，
We've already set the state to running,
所以状态是运行中。
so just the states running.
我们可以看到这个线程将切换到哪里，
We can see where this thread is going to switch to
在调用 swtch 的第 475 行，
in the call to swtch line 475,
打印上下文保存的寄存器，
print this context the saved registers,
那么 ra 在哪里，
so where is the ra,
我们要调用 swtch ，
we're going to call swtch,
但是正如我们知道的， swtch 返回，
but switch as we know it returns,
当它返回时，返回到恢复的 ra ，
when it returns it returns to the restore ra,
所以我们关心的是 ra 指向哪里，
so we really care about is where is it that ra points to,
我们可以通过以下方式找出。
we can find that out by.
糟糕。
Oops.
使用 x/i ，
Using x/i,
它返回 ra 指向某个点，
it's going to return ra points to some point instead,
这并不令人惊讶，
that's not too surprising,
假设另一个 spin 进程由于定时器中断而挂起，
presumably that other spin process was suspended due to a timer interrupt,
我们知道调用 sched ，调用 swtch 。
which as we know called sched, what's called swtch.
好了，现在要调用 swtch 了，
Alright, so about to call swtch,
让我再次打开 swtch 代码。
let me just bring up the swtch code again.
实际上在 swtch 中仍然，
Actually enter swtch were still,
仍然在调度器上下文中。
where shows that were still in the scheduler's context.
我要再次执行所有 swtch 的指令，
I want to again execute all of the instructions of swtch,
这次，从调度器切换到新进程。
this time switching from the scheduler to the new process.
我们跳过 28 个加载和保存。
We skip over the 28 stores and loads.
说服我们，要回到 sched 了，
Just convince ourselves that we are actually about to return to sched,
既然我们要返回 sched 而不是 scheduler ，
so now since we're about to return to sched and not scheduler,
我们现在必须在进程的内核线程中，
we must now be in a process's kernel thread
而不再是调度器线程，
and no longer the scheduler of thread,
事实上，如果我们查看 backtrace ，
indeed if we look at the backtrace,
我们有一个 usertrap 调用，
we had a usertrap call,
这一定是定时器中断，
that must have been a timer interrupt,
在过去的某个时候，
from long you know sometime in the past,
正如我们所看到的，调用 yield 和 sched ，
that as we've seen called yield and sched,
但它是定时器中断另一个进程，
but it was the timer interrupted the other process now,
不是在我们最初观察的进程中。
not in the process that we originally looked at.
好的，有什么问题吗，
Okay, any questions about,
我要停止一步步介绍代码了，
I think I'm gonna leave off stepping through the code at this point,
关于我们看过的任何材料，有什么问题吗。
any questions about any of the material we've seen.
不好意思，如果它是这样，比如这个[]，
Oh, sorry if it was, for example this [],
然后我们会看到 ra 会指向某个地方
then we would see that ra would point somewhere to
比如睡眠之类的，是吗？
like sleep or something like that, right.
嗯，是的。
Um, yes.
好的，我们在这里看到的 where ，
Well, we see that the where at this point
会包含一些系统调用实现函数，
would include some system call implementation functions
并且调用 sleep ，
and a call to sleep,
我想这是，
as it happens I think this is,
简单回答你的问题，是的，
you're basically answering questions, yes,
如果我们停止执行这个进程，
if we had just left off executing this process
因为不是定时器中断的原因，
for some reason other than the timer interrupt,
swtch 将返回到某些系统调用代码，而不是 sched ，
swtch would be basically returning to some system call code instead of to sched,
我认为 sleep 可能调用 sched ，所以。
as it happens I think sleep may call sched, so.
backtrace 看起来会不一样，
The backtrace would look different,
我想会包含 sched ，
what just happened include sched, I guess,
我只选择了一种方式，
I've chosen just one way of,
因为定时器中断而产生的进程切换。
you know just one way of switching between processes due to timer interrupts.
但是你也可以切换等待用户 IO ，
But you also get switches to wait for user IO,
等待其他进程执行比如写入管道的操作。
wait for other processes to do things like write to pipe.
好的，有一件事你可能会注意到，
Okay, one thing to you probably noticed is that
调度器调用 swtch ，
scheduler call swtch,
这里 swtch 返回的是什么，
and what about to return from swtch here,
但是我们是从一个不同的调用 swtch 返回，
but we're returning really from a different call to swtch
而不是调度器创建的，
than them on the scheduler are made,
我们是从这个进程很久以前调用 swtch 返回的。
we're returning from a call to swtch that this process made a long time ago.
所以，这可能有点令人困惑，
So, you know, this is potentially a little bit confusing,
但是，这就是线程切换[]的工作原理。
but, you know, this is how the [] of a thread switch work.
另一个需要注意的事情是，
Another thing to notice is that,
我们正在查看的代码，
the code we're looking at,
这个 swtch 代码，是线程切换的核心。
this swtch code, this is really the heart of thread switching.
你要切换线程所做的就是，
And really all you have to do to switch switch threads is
保存寄存器和恢复寄存器，
save registers and restore registers,
线程有比寄存器多的状态，
threads have a lot more state than just registers,
它们在堆里有变量和东西，
they have variables and stuff in the heap
无论什么，
and who knows what,
所有其他状态都在内存中，
all that other state is in-memory
不会受到干扰，
and isn't going to be disturbed,
我们没有做任何事情来干扰这些线程堆栈，
we've done nothing to disturb any of these threads stacks,
比如堆里的值，
for example or heap values,
所以微处理器的寄存器实际上是唯一一种易失性状态，
so the registers in the microprocessor are really the only kind of volatile state,
需要保存和恢复才能进行线程切换，
that actually needs to be saved and restored to do a thread switch,
内存堆栈中的所有内容，
all the stuffs in memory stack, for example,
仍会在内存中原封不动，
will still be in memory on undisturbed
所以，它不需要显式地保存和恢复。
and so it doesn't have to be explicitly saved and restored.
我们只保存和恢复微处理器 CPU 寄存器，
Now we're only saving and restoring this microprocessor, the CPU registers,
因为我们想为新线程重新使用这些寄存器，
because we want to reuse those [] registers in the CPU for the new thread
覆盖它们包含的任何值。
and overwrite whatever values they have.
所以，这就是为什么我们必须保存旧线程的寄存器。
So, register, that's why we have to save the old thread's registers.
那么，其他处理器的状态呢，
What about, other processors state,
我不知道我们使用的 RISC-V 处理器有没有其他标志，
so I don't know the RISC-V processor that we're using has other flags,
但我知道有些 x86 英特尔芯片有浮点单元状态
but I know like some x86 Intel chips have like like the floating point unit state
或类似的东西，
and like things like that,
在 RISC-V 中有没有这个？
do we do we just not have that in RISC-V?
你的观点在其他微处理器如 x86 上得到了很好的[理解]，
Your point's very well taken on other microprocessors like x86,
切换的细节略有不同，
the details switching are a bit different,
因为它们在不同的状态有不同的寄存器，
because they have different registers in different state
所以这是非常依赖于 RISC-V 的代码，
and so the code this is very very RISC-V dependent code
对于其他处理器，切换程序可能看起来不同，
and the switch routine for some other processor might look quite different,
比如可能必须保存浮点寄存器，
like indeed might have to save floating point registers,
RISC-V 使用的是通用寄存器。
you know RISC-V actually uses the general purpose registers.
实际上，我不确定它对浮点数有什么作用，
Actually, I'm not sure what it does for floating point,
但是内核不使用浮点，
but the kernel doesn't use floating point,
所以不用担心它，
so you don't have to worry about it,
但是，是的，这完全依赖于微处理器。
but yeah this is totally microprocessor dependent.
一个关于定时器中断的问题。
A question about the timer interrupts.
所以听起来像是所有调度工作的核心是，
So it sounds like the the core of all of this scheduling working is that
有一个定时器中断，
there will be a timer interrupt,
如果它出现故障会发生什么？
what happens in cases where that malfunctions.
这里会有一个定时器中断。
There is going to be a timer interrupt.
所以，我知道，
So the, I know so,
好的，用户进程的抢占式调度能起作用的原因是，
okay, so the reasoning for how come preemptive scheduling of user process's works is
用户进程总是在打开中断的情况下执行，
that user processes execute with interrupts turned on always,
xv6 确保在返回用户空间之前启用中断，
xv6 just ensures that interrupts are enabled before returning to user space
这意味着如果在用户空间中执行，可以发生定时器中断，
and that means that a timer interrupt can happen if you're executing in user space,
所以用户进程不可能，
so there's nothing a user process,
如果在用户空间，定时器中断就会发生，
if on user space that timer interrupt just will happen,
当时间到来的时候。
when the time comes.
所以，在内核中有一点微妙之处，
So a little trickier in the kernel,
内核有时会关闭中断，
the kernel sometimes turns off interrupts,
比如，当你获取锁的时候，
like when you acquire a lock,
中断将被关闭，
the interrupts are going to be turned off,
直到你释放它。
until you release it.
所以。
So.
所以，如果内核中有一些 bug ，
So if there were some bugs in the kernel,
如果内核关闭中断，
if the kernel turned off interrupts
没有再打开它们，
and never turn them back on
内核中的代码不会放弃 CPU ，
and the code in the kernel never gave up the CPU
从来没有调用 sleep ，
never called sleep,
或者因为任何其他原因放弃 CPU ，
gave up the CPU for any other reason,
那么会发生计时器中断，
then indeed timer interrupt would occur
这意味着，
and that would mean that,
这个内核代码，可能永远不会放弃 CPU ，
this kernel code, may you know, would never give the CPU,
但是，据我们所知， xv6 []，
but in fact, as far as we know xv6 [] xv6,
所以它总是重新打开中断，
so that it always turns interrupts back on,
或者，如果在 xv6 中有关闭中断的代码，
or you know, if there's code in xv6, it turns off interrupts,
它必须重新打开中断，
it has to turns them back on
所以定时器中断可以在内核中发生，
and so timer interrupt can then occur in the kernel,
我们可以从这个内核线程切换，
and we can switch away from this kernel thread
或者代码返回到用户空间，
or the code returns back to user space,
内核代码返回到用户空间，
kernel code turns back to user space,
我们相信不会出现这种情况，
we believe there's never a situation
内核代码在中断关闭的情况下永远循环。
in which kernel code will simply like loop with interrupts turned off forever.
我知道了，我的问题更多的是关于，
I got, my question was more about like,
所以我假设中断来自某个硬件，
so I assume the interrupts are actually coming from some piece of hardware,
如果那个硬件出现故障。
what if that piece of hardware malfunctions.
不。
No.
没关系，那是你的电脑坏了，你应该买一台新的。
It's all right, then your computer is broken, you should buy a new one.
好的。
Okay.
我是说，这是一个合理的问题，
I mean that's a valid question for,
你的计算机里有 100 亿个晶体管，
there's you know 10 billion transistors in your computer,
的确，有时硬件会有 bug ，
and indeed sometimes the hardware just like has bugs in it,
但这超出了我们的范围。
but that's beyond our reach for.
我是说，如果你计算 1+1 ，而电脑给出 3，
I mean, if you add 1 and 1 and the computer says 3,
那么你遇到深层次的问题，
then you just have deep problems,
xv6 不能帮你解决。
that xv6 can't help you with.
所以，我们假设计算机是可以工作的。
So we're assuming that the computer works.
唯一一次，软件可以，
The only time when that when software,
我是说，有时软件会试图弥补硬件错误，
I mean, there are times when software tries to compensate for hardware level errors,
比如，如果你通过网络发送数据包，
like if you're sending packets across the network,
总是发送校验和，
you always send a checksum,
如果网络硬件翻转了一个位，
so that if the network hardware flips a bit,
出现故障翻转了一个位，
malfunctions flips a bit,
那么你可以纠正这个，
then you can correct that,
但是对于计算机里的东西，
but for stuff inside the computer,
人们往往不会，
people tend not to,
它只是，
it's just,
人们不会试图让软件来弥补硬件错误。
people basically don't try to make the software compensate for hardware errors.
我有个问题，
Oh, I have a question,
为什么在 trampoline. ，在 swtch 中，
why so like in trampoline dot, actually in swtch,
我们用汇编语言编写代码，
we write the code in assembly,
这是因为，
is that why,
是不是因为我们要确保这件事的发生，
is that because we want to make sure that exactly this thing happen,
所以我们不能用 C 写，
so we cannot, you cann't write in C,
因为我们需要，
because we just need,
[感觉]这些事情发生。
it feels like those exact things to happen basically.
是的，是的。
Yeah yeah.
是的，我们当然希望这个确切的顺序发生，
Yes, certainly we want this exact sequence to happen,
C 很难访问像 ra 或 sp 这样的东西，
and C it it's very hard to talk about things like ra in C or sp
当然，在 C 语言中，也没有办法
certainly there's no way within the C language
使用 ra 寄存器访问修改堆栈指针，
to talk about changing the stack pointer with ra register,
这些东西不能在普通的 C 中看到，
so these are things that, just can't be you can't see it in ordinary C,
你能在 C 中看到它的唯一方式是，
the only way you can see it in C is
在 C 代码中嵌入汇编语言指令，
there, there is possible in C to sort of embed assembly instructions in C code,
所以我们可以把这些汇编指令嵌入到 C 函数中，
so we could have just embedded these assembly instructions in the C function,
但是，这就等同于一件事了。
but, would amount to the same thing.
我们是在低于 C 的级别下操作的，
We're basically we're operating at a level below below C,
所以我们不能在这里使用 C 。
so we can't really can't really use C here.
我有个问题，
I have a question,
关于当线程完成执行，
about when a thread finishes executing
假设发生在用户空间，
and assuming that happens in the user space
当我们调用 exec 系统调用，
when we call the exec, I'm sorry, [exec] system call
它也结束了进程，
and that also ends the process,
在内核空间的线程，
the thread assuming in the kernel space,
但是如果线程在新的定时器中断发生之前结束，
but if the thread ends within before a new timer interrupt happens,
它是否还是，
does it still look like,
比如 CPU 还在被那个线程获取，
is this like the CPU still acquire by that thread
或者结束那个线程并开始一个新的，
or do we end that thread and start a new one
在新的定时器中断之前。
before the new timer interrupt.
是的,
Oh yeah,
线程让出 CPU ，
the thread, the thread yields the CPU,
exec 让出 CPU ，
there's the exec exec yields the CPU,
所以实际上有很多点，
so there's actually many points,
尽管我一直在用定时器中断来讨论，
that even though I've been driving this discussion with a timer interrupt,
事实上，在几乎所有的情况下，
in fact, in almost almost all cases
xv6 在线程之间切换，
where xv6 switches between threads,
不是由于定时器中断，
it's not due to timer interrupts,
因为有些系统调用在等待某些东西，
it's because some system calls waiting for something
决定需要放弃 CPU ，
or decides that it needs to give up the CPU
比如， exec 执行各种操作，
and so for example exec does various things
然后调用 yield 并放弃 CPU ，
and then calls yield to give up the CPU
它就是这么做的，
and it does that, there's really nothing,
独立去做，与定时器中断无关。
does that independently of whether there's timer interrupt.
是的。
Yes.
好了，这节课的时间到了，
All right, the time is up for this lecture,
我想下周我会继续讨论这个问题，
I think I'll continue some of this discussion next week,
但是我现在很乐意回答更多的问题，
but I'm happy to take more questions right now,
如果人们有问题的话。
if people have them.
那么，让我们说操作系统，
So let's say the operating system,
实际上，我采用了线程实现，
actually I takes on a the thread implementation,
比如，你希望在多个 CPU 上运行一个进程的多个线程，
so so for example you want to run multiple threads of a process on multiple CPUs,
这必须由操作系统来处理，
like that has to be handled by the OS,
不能在用户空间中处理，是吗？
that cannot just be handled in user space, right?
这种切换是怎么工作的，
How does that kind of switching work
是每个线程都变成了一个进程，
is each, each thread now becomes the same as a process,
比如，在所有现有线程中循环，
like is always going to loop through all existing threads
或者，因为每个 CPU 仍然会切换，
or you know because like each CPU will still switch between,
即使一个进程提供八个核心，
even if one process give eight cores,
它还会在这些 CPU 之间切换，
like it's still gonna switch switch each of the CPUs between those
以及其他一些进程，
and a couple of other processes
而且我们也不想，在同一个 CPU 上的切换一个线程和另一个线程，
and also we don't want to really
switch between one and the other thread on the same CPU
或者我们希望，我不知道。
or do we, I don't know.
等等，我能不能。
Wait, can I.
我不确定问题是什么。
I'm not sure what the question is.
是的，我想，
Yeah, I guess I guess,
你能解释一下这是怎么发生的吗？
can you just explain more like how does that happen.
抱歉，什么是怎么发生的。
Sorry, how does what happened.
假设每个进程有多个线程，
Let's say we have multiple threads per process,
它们可以在不同的 CPU 上运行，
so that they can and they can run on different CPUs,
我们如何处理这些。
like how do we go, how do you go about there.
比如， Linux 支持每个进程多个线程，
So Linux, for example supports multiple threads per process
在 Linux 中，是一个很复杂的实现，
and in Linux, the implementation, it's a complex implementation,
也许最简单的解释是，
but maybe the simplest way to explain it is that,
几乎 Linux 中的每个线程都是一个完整的进程，
each, it's almost as if each thread in Linux is a complete process,
给定进程的线程，
and the the threads of a given,
我们称之为特定进程的线程，
what we would call the threads of a particular process
本质上是共享内存的独立进程，
are essentially separate processes that share the same memory,
所以 Linux 在某种程度上将执行线程的概念从地址空间中分离出来，
so Linux has sort of separated out the notion of thread of execution from address space
你可以把它们独立起来，
and you know you can have them separately,
如果在一个进程中有两个线程，
and if you make two threads in one process,
它基本上是两个进程共享一个地址空间，
it basically makes two processes that share one address space,
从那时起，
and then from then on,
调度与 xv6 对各个进程所做的没有什么不同。
the scheduling is not unlike what xv6 does for individual processes.
我明白了，然后，有没有什么东西，
I see and then is there anything,
比如用户必须指定，
like does the user have to specify,
每个线程要固定到一个 CPU 上，
like okay pin each thread to a CPU
或者操作系统如何确保
or how does the OS make sure
同一进程的不同线程不会在同一核心上运行，
that different threads of the same process don't run on the same core,
因为这是不是违反了目的，
because that's kind of defeating the purpose,
或者不是，我猜的，我不知道。
or not, I guess, I don't know.
这个其实跟 xv6 很像，就是，
The the, it's actually just like it's much like xv6, namely the,
这里有四个核心，
you know there's four cores
Linux 只会为这四个核心中找到四个东西，
and Linux will just find four things for one of those four cores,
如果没有太多的事情发生，
they maybe, you know if there's not much going on,
那么可能会是同一进程的四个线程，
then maybe they'll be four threads of the same process,
或者如果有一百个用户登录到 Athena 机器，
or if there's a hundred users logged in on Athena machine,
也许是每个线程来自多个不同的进程，
maybe it's one thread each from multiple different processes,
没有一个固定答案，
you know, there's not any one answer
或者内核为每个核心找到要做的事情，
or the kernel basically find something for each core to do
然后那个核心做那件事。
and then that core does that thing.
好的，理解了。
Okay, that makes sense.
如果你想仔细测量，
You can, you know if you're if you want to do careful measurements,
有一种方法可以将线程固定在核心上，
there is a way to pin threads to cores,
但是人们只有在做一些奇怪的事情时才会这么做。
but people only do it when they're up to something strange.
所以是共享虚拟表。
So you share the virtual table.
你能再说一遍吗？
Can you say it again.
虚拟内存。
Virtual memory.
所以说哪些线程有相同的页表。
So they say they have the same page table, those threads.
是的，如果你在 Linux 上，在一个进程中创建两个线程，
Yeah yeah, if you're on Linux, if you create two threads in one process,
然后你就有了两个线程。
then you have these two threads.
我不知道它们是否共享完全相同的页表，
I don't know if they like literally share the exact same page table
或者它们的页表是相同的，
or whether their page tables are identical,
两个中的一个。
one or the other.
有没有原因让它们分开，
Is there a reason why they would have to be separate, ever,
如果你手动映射内存，或者。
if you manually map memory, or.
我不知道 Linux 是哪种。
I I don't know enough to know whether which which Linux does.
好的，我还有一个关于一个小细节的问题，
Okay, I have another question about a small detail,
根据我的理解，当你调用 swtch 时，
so basically like from my understanding when you call swtch,
从一个调用切换到另一个，
you switch from one call to switch to another,
所以当你第一次调用 swtch 时，
so the first time you call swtch,
必须人为地创建返回的端点，是吧。
you have to like kind of artificially create other endpoint to come back to, right.
是的。
Yes.
因为你不能随便跳到任何代码。
Because you can't just randomly jump in to [] any code.
是的，你想知道那个伪造在哪里，
Yes, you want to know where that, where that fake,
那个上下文是在哪里创造的。
where that context was cooked up.
我猜可能是在进程创建的地方，
Probably somewhere where the process is created, I guess,
我不知道。
I don't know.
是的，可能是 userinit ，
Yeah yeah, maybe userinit,
没有使用 allocproc 。
or not using allocproc.
我也不知道。
I don't know.
有一个叫做 fork trap 的东西。
There's something called fork trap or something.
是的，看这个，有 forkret ，
Yeah, look at this, yeah we got forkret,
好的，所以 allocproc ，
okay so an allocproc
在引导时的第一个进程或 fork 时调用，
which is called both for the very first process at boot time and by fork,
allocproc 为新进程设置上下文的关键元素，
allocproc sets up the critical elements of the context for the new processes,
它设置了新进程的上下文，
it, it sets up the new process's context,
大多数寄存器是什么并不重要，
it actually doesn't matter what most of the registers are,
但重要的是 ra 是什么，
but it does matter what ra is,
因为第一个 swtch ，
because that's where the swtch the very first swtch
那个进程会返回到 ra ，
and that process is going to return to ra,
那个进程需要使用自己的堆栈，
And that process is going to need to use its own stack,
所以 ra 和 sp 设置，是伪造的，
so ra and sp setup, faked essentially,
所以，第一个 swtch 或进程可以正常工作。
so the very first swtch or process works.
所以，如果我理解正确的话，
So, so if I understand this correctly,
当这个 swtch 发生时，
when this swtch will happen,
它会开始执行 forkret 内部的第一条指令，
then it'll basically just start executing the first instruction inside of the forkret,
forkret 调用 swtch ，再返回。
as if forkret just called swtch and return from.
是的，从 swtch 返回跳到 forkret 的开头。
Yeah yeah, the return from switch is gonna be jump to the beginning of forkret.
好的，有意思，
Alright, interesting,
我们有没有调用 forkret ，还是总是这样，
do we ever call forkret or is it always happens,
我想总是这样发生的。
I think it always happens like this.
我不认为有什么东西调用了 forkret ，
I don't think anything ever calls forkret for [],
因为，
because just,
是的，它只在第一个进程运行时以这种奇怪的方式执行。
yeah it's only executed in this weird way from first [] process is run.
它的工作实际上是释放调度器占用的锁，
It is really its job is to release the lock the scheduler took
然后返回，
and then return
然后这个 usertrapret ，当然，也是伪造的。
and then this usertrapret, of course, is also fake.
它是，
That it's, it's,
就像是从 trap 返回，
yeah it's like it's as if returning from a trap,
trapframe 也是伪造的，
except the trapframe is faked also,
调到用户代码的第一个指令。
to to have like jump to the first instruction in the user code.
但是 trapframe ，
Oh, but the trapframe,
它又是一样，不需要初始化任何寄存器，
it's again the same like you don't need to initialize any registers,
因为就像我们要从头开始，
because it's like well we're going to the beginning,
所以你不需要假设任何事。
so you don't need to assume anything.
是的，程序计数器我认为是。
Yeah, the program counter I think is.
是的。
Yeah.
它需要初始化为零，
It needs to be initialized to zero,
我不知道还有什么，
I don't know what else,
也许就是它。
you maybe maybe it.
它们可能，如果我们调用它们不正确，
They probably if we call them it doesn't right,
因为如果我们已经进行了调用，
because if we already do the call,
那么就会设置程序计数器。
then that's going to set the program counter.
是的，只会在这里发生，
Yeah, so here's this only happens,
是因为 fork 复制了程序计数器，
because fork copies, fork copies the program counter,
用户程序计数器，
the user program counter
所以我们唯一不做 fork 的是，
and so the only time when we're not doing fork is
对于第一个进程，
for the very first process
在那里它明显的欺骗性的。
where it's like explicitly deceptive.
噢。
Oh.
而且堆栈指针。
And stack pointer.
哦，是的。
Oh yeah.
也需要设置。
Also needs to be set up.
是的，因为它是 EPC 不是 PC ，
Oh yeah, because it's that EPC that's not PC,
就是那个要被 trampoline 换掉的。
that's the one that's gonna get swapped by the trap trampoline.
是的。
Yes.
哦，我明白了。
Oh, I see.
因为真正的程序计数器会在 trampoline 中，
Because the real PC is actually gonna be in trap like inside trampoline,
但是我们要把它切换，跳到那里。
but then we're gonna switch it to jump to there.
是的。
Yeah.
我能不能问一下，
Can I just ask,
你能不能回到 allocproc 。
like can you go back to the allocproc.
我觉得这里，
I think there's,
哦，不是，抱歉，是 forkret ，
oh no sorry, forkret
那里有一些东西我想只发生在第一个进程。
there is something there, that happens I think for the first process only.
对于第一个调用，我不太确定发生了什么事。
What's this for a first call, I wasn't really sure what happened.
我们看看，
Let's see,
文件系统需要初始化，
the file system, the file system needs to be initialized
特别是一些内容需要从磁盘上读取，
and in particular some stuff needs to be read off the disk
为了使文件系统运行，
in order to get the file system going,
比如有一种叫做超级块，
like there's this thing called the super block,
用来描述文件系统有多大，
which describes how big the file system are,
以及文件系统中各种内容的位置，
and where the various things are in the file system
还有一个崩溃恢复日志，
and there's also a crash recovery log,
需要重播，
that needs to be replayed
以便从之前的崩溃中恢复过来，
in order to recover from a previous crash,
如果有的话。
if there was one.
但是为了在文件系统中执行任何操作，
But in order to do anything in the file system,
你需要等待磁盘操作完成，
you need to be able to wait for disk operations to complete,
但是 xv6 的工作方式，
but the way xv6 works,
你只能在进程的上下文中执行文件系统代码，
you really can only execute the file system code in the context of process,
为了比如等待 IO ，
in order to like wait for IO
所以文件系统的初始化必须推迟，
and so therefore the initialization of the file system has to be deferred
直到我们有一个进程在运行。
until the first time we have a process running.
这发生在 forkret 的第一个进程中。
And that occurs in the very first process in forkret.
我明白了。
I see.
我猜我们稍后会对此有更多了解。
And I'm guessing we'll learn more about this later.
是的，不是关于这个烂摊子，
Yeah, not about this horrible mess,
而是关于文件系统是如何工作的。
but about how file systems work.
好的，谢谢，
All right okay well, thank you,
抱歉占用您时间了。
I'm sorry for holding on so long.
谢谢你的回答。
Thanks for all the answers.
抱歉，是不是在初始化个进程，
Sorry, it that init that process,
当这个东西被执行的时候……
when this thing is executed...